<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Meditations and deuout discourses vpon the B. Sacrament composed by Ch. M.</title>
            <author>Ch. M.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1639</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 182 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 122 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06674</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17128</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S909</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">23025767</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 23025767</idno>
            <idno type="VID">26101</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06674)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 26101)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1778:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Meditations and deuout discourses vpon the B. Sacrament composed by Ch. M.</title>
                  <author>Ch. M.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>14, [14], 190 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By L. Kellam,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at Doway :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1639.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: a⁴ b⁶, ²a⁴ A-Z⁴ 2A³.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. 14 at beginning.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: tightly bound with slight loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
                  <note>Includes bibliographical references.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lord's Supper --  Meditations.</term>
               <term>Meditations --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Corinne Vieracker</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Corinne Vieracker</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:26101:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26101:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>MEDITATIONS, AND DEVOVT DISCOVRSES VPON THE B. SACRAMENT <hi>COMPOSED BY</hi> Ch. M.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Caro mea verè eſt cibus,</l>
               <l>&amp; ſanguis meus verè eſt potus.</l>
               <l>My Fleſh is meate indeed,</l>
               <l>and my blood is drink indeed.</l> 
               <bibl>IOAN 6.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Printed at DOWAY by L. KELLAM, Anno 1639.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:26101:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26101:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE AND VERTVOVS LADIE THE LADIE CECILIE, COVNTESSE AND DOWAGER OF THE LATE EARLE OF RVTLAND.</head>
            <p>WRITERS of bookes (moſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Ladie) are ſpirituall parents, and their bookes are their broods, &amp; young-ones. And therefore, as carnall parents
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:26101:3"/>haue no ſooner a child borne to the world, but they looke about them for a ſecondarie Father or Mother (whom they ſtile Godfather and Godmother) by whoſe name the child may be graced, and by whoſe authoritie it may be protected: So writers of books are no ſooner deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered of theſe their young<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ones, the broods of their braines, and fruitfull vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings, but they by and by thinke of a Patron or Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troneſſe, to whom they may commend them: whoſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, becauſe they are
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:26101:3"/>common, I being not vnwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to follow, had no ſooner finished this litle Pamphlet of meditations on the B. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament (my young Benia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min borne to me in my old age) but I bethought myſelf to whoſe Patronage, and tui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I might beſt commend it. And my cogitation did preſentlie light, and hitt vpon your Honour, who by your great nobilitie (as being dowager to the Illuſtrious Earle of Rutland, Siſter to the Lord Nicholas Tufton can grace it, by your credit
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:26101:4"/>by your credit (as being of our prime nobilitie) can pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect it, by your pietie will imbrace it, &amp; by your manie noble fauours may challenge it. Let others dedicate their Annales and Hiſtories of warres and Martiall feates to Kings and Emperours: I will preſume to offer a booke of Pietie to a Ladie moſt noble and pious, and yet ſo pious that her pietie graceth her nobilitie. Your Honour ſince the death of your noble Husband, the Illuſtrious Earle of Rutland, hath im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced the ſtate of a widow,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:26101:4"/>the moſt noble ſtate &amp; moſt pleaſing to God after Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginitie, in which you haue carried your ſelf ſo like your ſelf, that you deſerue Honour of all, according to that of the Apoſtle <hi>Honour widowes, which are widowes indeed.</hi> You imitate by your retired life that famous widow <hi>Iudith, who in the Higher partes of her houſe, made herſelf a ſecret chamber,</hi> in which she liued retiredlie with her maids, ſeruing God by praier and faſting: yea you follow the example of the widow and Propheteſſe <hi>Anna,</hi> whom
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:26101:5"/>the Euangeliſt commendeth <hi>for that she departed not from the Temple, but by fasting and prayer ſerued God.</hi> For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though your Honour wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth not goodlie Houſes, Parkes, and Gardens, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you may recreate your ſelf, yet to shew your ſelf a <hi>widow indeed,</hi> you haue made choiſe of your Oratorie for your Pallace and cheefe place of aboade, and from thence you hardlie depart, becauſe there you co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſe with God, and he with you, and when there you reade your Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall books, he talketh
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:26101:5"/>with you, and when you pray, you talke with him. And although you keepe an Honourable Table, ſuting with your nobilitie, yet the fare which moſt pleaſeth you, is <hi>Judithes</hi> and <hi>Annaes</hi> fare, to wit, faſting, which is the foode of the Soule, and the Phyſick of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, which ſo weakeneth the body, as it ſtrengthneth the ſoule. And although your Honour wanteth nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther lands nor liuings, nor reuenewes, which the world calleth Riches, yet you eſteeme Almeſdeeds your
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:26101:6"/>greateſt treaſures, as indeed they are. For as Marchants when they haue laied out all their monies, do then eſteeme themſelues richeſt, becauſe they expect greater and richer marchandiſes; ſo your Honour is the richer by your Almeſdeeds, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe by this laying out, you purchaſe greater treaſures in heauen. So that, although you be a widow, in reſpect of your late moſt noble Husband, yet you are no widow in reſpect of Chriſt, to whom you are eſpouſed, not onelie by faith, hope,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:26101:6"/>and charitie, as all good chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians are, but in a more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect manner, by renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing all marriage with man on Earth, to marrie and vnite your ſelf more neer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie to your Spouſe God and man in Heauen: <hi>Not thinking</hi> now (to vſe th' Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles words) <hi>on things that pertaine to the world, as the married woeman doth, how to pleaſe an husband, but thinking on the things that pertaine to our lord how to pleaſe him.</hi> And therefore he now is your ſpouſe, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you loue aboue all, on whom your loue is
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:26101:7"/>ſetled, on whom your thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghts are fixed, to whom all your actions are directed: he is euer in your minde, euer in your thought, euer in your memorie: and that time which other Ladies ſpend in adorning them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, ſo to pleaſe their Husbands, you ſpend, in adorning your ſoule, by prayer, meditation, faſting, Almes-deeds, and other vertues, ſo to pleaſe your Spouſe Chriſt Ieſus. He therefore, who hath eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pouſed you to him in Earth, by his grace, eſpouſe you
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:26101:7"/>alſo vnto him in heauen, by his glorie, and in the meane time heape many benedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions vpon you. So deſireth, ſo prayeth.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>YOVR HONOVRS <hi>Humble ſeruant</hi> CH. M.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:26101:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>FAVLT'S ESCAPED IN THE PRINTINGE.</head>
            <list>
               <item>In the praeface to the Reader n. 11.</item>
               <item>Sacraments. Cor. Sacrament.</item>
               <item>Pag. 8. lin. 16. tuee. Cor. thee.</item>
               <item>Pag. 15. li. 17. truobled. Cor. troubled.</item>
               <item>Pag. 20. lin. 9. Ioſeth. Cor. Ioſeph.</item>
               <item>Pag. 21. lin. vlt. tall. Cor. tell.</item>
               <item>Pag. 27. lin. vlt. hed. Cor. shed.</item>
               <item>Pag. 45. lin. 21. ſayinſt. Cor. ſaying.</item>
               <item>Pag. 53. in margine lib 61. Correct hom. 61.</item>
               <item>Pag. 170. lin. 6. &amp; 17. Manha. Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect Manhu.</item>
               <item>Pag. 189. lin. 10, fare. Cor. Farre.</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:26101:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:26101:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26101:9"/>
            <head>The Contents of the MEDITATIONS</head>
            <list>
               <item>THE FIRST MEDITATION. What loue Chriſt shewed at his laſt ſupper.</item>
               <item>THE SECOND MEDITATIONS. What charitie and humilitie Chriſt shewed before he ſatte downe to his laſt ſupper.</item>
               <item>THE THIRD MEDITATION How bountiful a Feaſt-maker and Hoſt Chriſt shewed him ſelf, and how great a feaſt he exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited to his diſciples, in the B. Sacrament.</item>
               <item>THE FOVRTH MEDITATION. How prouident a paterfamilias &amp; Good man of the Howſe of our ſoule and the Church, Chriſt is by this B Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:26101:10"/>
               <item>THE FIFTH MEDITATION. How Chriſt shewed himſelfe in this B. Sacrament a Father, and more then a Father vnto vs.</item>
               <item>THE SIXT MEDITATION. How Chriſt shewed himſelfe in the B. Sacrament a Mother, and more then a Mother.</item>
               <item>THE SEAVENTH MEDITATION. What a Freind Chriſt hath shewed himſelfe in the B. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament.</item>
               <item>THE EIGHT MEDITATION. How Chriſt hath shewed himſelfe in this B. Sacrament, a moſt louing ſpouſe.</item>
               <item>THE NINTH MEDITATION. What a Phyſician Chriſt hath shewed himſelf in this B. Sacrament.</item>
               <item>THE TENTH MEDITATION. How good a shepheard and Paſtour Chriſt hath shewed himſelfe in this B. Sacrament.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:26101:10"/>
               <item>THE II. MEDITATION. With what feare, and reuerence, &amp; acknowledgment of vnworthines, the deuout receiuer is to come to this B. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament.</item>
               <item>THE XII. MEDITATION With what loue to our Sauiour Wee should receiue this B. Sacrament.</item>
               <item>THE XIII. MEDITATION. To bee made immediatlie after communion: How thankefull the Receiuer should bee.</item>
               <item>THE XIV. MEDITATION How the Communicant or Receiuer is enriched by this B. Sacrament, and ſoe should little eſteeme all worldlie loſſes.</item>
               <item>THE XV. MEDITATION. How by the receiuing of this B. Sacrament the Receiuer is made the Temple of God.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:26101:11"/>
               <item>THE XVI. MEDITATION. Of the good purpoſes which after Communion are to bee made.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="approbation">
            <head>APPROBATIO.</head>
            <p>HAE meditationes Euchariſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cae Ch. M. piae ſunt &amp; deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae, nihil fidei catholicae &amp; bonis moribus contrarium continentes, ideoque vtiliter excudentur &amp; perlegentur. Actum Duaci 4. Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lij 1639.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Georgius Coluenerius S. Theol. Doctor, &amp; Regius, ordinariuſque ac primarius Profeſſor Duacen ſis Vniuerſitatis Cancellarius, &amp; li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brorum Cenſor.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:26101:11"/>
            <head>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>o the Reader.</head>
            <p>THE nature of man is deſirous of No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueltie, chaunge, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> &amp; varietie. Noe bed is ſo ſoft, of which in tyme we are not wearie; no Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick ſo delightfull, which by ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> repetition, becommeth not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious: noe diſh ſo daintie which if it come often to the table is not loathed: and nothing but the cleare viſion and fruition of God doth alwaies content.</p>
            <p>The reaſon of this is the ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciencie of God his goodnes &amp; the inſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie of that which is good in his creatures. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> For God is <hi> Su<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mum bonum,</hi> cheefeſt and infinite Good
<pb facs="tcp:26101:12"/>in which is no defect, and ſo being ſeen clearlie, &amp; perfectli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, as he is of the Bleſſed in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who ſee him <hi>face to face,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.</note> doth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies delight, neuer glutte the Bleſſed, or make them deſirous of chaunge. But all creatures, and create Goods, as they content and delight for a tyme, by reaſon that they are good in their kind, ſo in tyme they diſcontent, and make vs wearie of them, becauſe in that they are finite, they are alſo defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient. VVhence it is that as ſick men cannot lye long on one ſide or in one poſture, but doe turn &amp; chaunge often, ſo wee are neuer long content with any one create thing, ſeeme it at firſt neuer ſo pleaſing, but after wee haue had a taſt of it, wee are wearie of it, and deſire to chaunge, though ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymes for worſe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> And this is the cauſe why after
<pb facs="tcp:26101:12"/>many ſpirituall bookes ſet out heretofore by others, I haue not feared to ſet out myne, though they bee of the ſame ſubiect that other former bookes were, ſeeing that, though myne treat of the ſame matter, yet they doe it in a diuers manner, and ſo for varietie may pleaſe. I knew well that many had written <hi>paraphraſes</hi> vpon the Pſalme <hi>Miſerere</hi> and vpon all the Pſalmes: and yet in the yeare 1635 ladue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tured to ſet out mine alſo, hoping that when deuout perso<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s are wearie of ſtill reading others <hi>Paraphraſes,</hi> they wold for va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rietie be content to read mine al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, and I was not deceiued.</p>
            <p>And although I was not igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant that many Authours haue written meditations vpon the B. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Sacrament, and the ſacred paſſion of Chriſt yet for the aforeſaid reaſon, I now diuulge my medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations
<pb facs="tcp:26101:13"/>vpon the ſame ſubiects, hoping that after often reading of thoſe former bookes, ſome out of deſire of chaunge wilbe content to read mine though inferiour.</p>
            <p>And therfore to accommodate my ſelf to humain infirmitie, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> to which euen ſpirituall exerciſes, in time grow weariſome, in theſe my meditations vpon the B. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, I haue ſo diſpoſed, that euerie meditation, hath a diuers particular ſubiect, that ſo the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rietie at leaſt may allure the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; and that the Communicant or Receiuer may come with a better ſpirituall appetite and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notion to receiue in this Holy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, his Sauiour &amp; his ſacred bodie and bloud, I propoſe him in diuers manners, as in manner, of a Feaſt maker, a bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tifull houſe keeper, a Freind, a Paſtour, a phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician,
<pb facs="tcp:26101:13"/>a ſpouſe, a Father, and the like, that this varietie may delight and cauſe the Receiuer to come to this Holie Sacrament without any tediouſnes, yea with greater ſpirituall appetite.</p>
            <p>And ſo I hope my meditations will not be vngratefull, becauſe in them there is varietie, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> and diuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie alſo from the meditations, which others haue ſet forth. others may haue ſomethi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, which I haue not, and I may haue ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, which they haue not; they may haue their manner, and I may haue myne; they may haue their inuentions, I may haue myne; and ſo both theirs and myne may be pleaſing. For as the ſame meate di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſlie cooked, may be as pleaſing as diuers meates, ſoe the ſame mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter handled by diuers diuerſlie may by reaſon of this varietie, prooue no leſſe pleaſing then di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers
<pb facs="tcp:26101:14"/>matters, and ſubiectes.</p>
            <p>Otherwiſe, if becauſe that ſome haue written of a ſubiect, others who ſucceed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, muſt not touch that matter, all modern Authours muſt abſteine from writing, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe nothing can be now ſayd, which was not in ſubſtance ſayd before. For as <hi>Eccleſiaſtes</hi> ſaid in his time, ſo much more may wee now ſay in our time:
<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 1</note> 
               <hi>nothing vnder the Sunne is new, neither is any man able to ſaye: behold this is new; for that it hath alreadie gone before in the ages that were before.</hi> And ſo wee See that there are diuers commenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries vpon the ſame booke of ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, diuers ſermons on the ſame holy day &amp; text, diuers bookes of the ſame part of Philoſophie &amp; diuinitie.</p>
            <p>This being premiſed for my ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> I will breeflie aduertiſe the Reader that Meditation is not
<pb facs="tcp:26101:14"/>whatſoeuer ſpeculation or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe vpon God or his diuine perfections, or the myſteries of our faith, for, this ſpeculation being only to diſcouer the truth, is not worthie the name of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation, which is a kind of men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal prayer: but meditation doth ſpeculate the aforeſaid obiectes, &amp; diſcourſeth on them to mooue ſome affection, as loue, ioye, feare, ſorrow, according to the natures of the myſteries or obiectes, on which wee meditate. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> 
            </p>
            <p>In this exerciſe of meditation (as the contemplatiues doe well obſerue) there are three wayes to perfection. The one is <hi>Purgatiue,</hi> when by meditation wee ſtirr vp in vs a feare of God &amp; his Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and ſorrow for our ſinnes or hatred of them, by which our ſoules are purged from all filth of ſinne. The ſecond way is <hi>illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natiue,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:26101:15"/>when by meditation our underſtanding is ſo illuminated, as it ſeeth the excellencie of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, as of obedience, humilitie, pouertie of ſpirit, chaſtitie and the like, and ſeing the beautie of it, induceth the will to loue it, and louing it, to practiſe and to get it. The third way is <hi>Vnitiue,</hi> when by meditation of God his Diuine perfections we ſtirre vp in our heartes a loue of God, a compla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence in his Goodnes or mercie, or other his perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and diuine attributes &amp; by this way our ſoules are vnited to God. The firſt way is of beginners, the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of thoſe that profit in the way of vertue, the third of them that are perfect.</p>
            <p>In my <hi>Paraphraſis</hi> and medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Pſalme <hi>Miſerere,</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> I haue ſpeciallie ſhewed the <hi>Purgatiue</hi> way, inducing the ſinner to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance and ſorrow for his ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,
<pb facs="tcp:26101:15"/>by which ſorrow the ſoule is purged fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſinne. In my medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions vpon the Paſſion, I propoſe the <hi>illuminatiue</hi> waye, becauſe Chriſt in his Paſſion hath ſet vs exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples of all vertues. In my me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s vpon the B. Sacrament I teach the <hi>vnitiue</hi> way, that Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by it ſelfe vniting vs reallie to Chriſt, and the conſideration of it ſtirring vp loue towards God for ſuch a benefit, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> by which we are vnited vnto him; although in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed in euerie one of theſe my treatiſes, I ſhew all the aforeſayd three wayes.</p>
            <p>But becauſe Chriſt inſtituted this B. Sacrament before his Paſſion, and was immolated my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticallie before he was ſacrificed on the Croſſe reallie: I firſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent thee (Gentle Reader) with my Meditations on the B. Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and after them I will make
<pb facs="tcp:26101:16"/>thee partaker of thoſe of the Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion which ſhall follow theſe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer. God graunt that both thou and I, in them may find out and follow the aforeſayd three wayes to perfection; that wee may at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to the perfection of vertue and grace in this life, and ſoe to the perfection of glorie (which is our laſt and greateſt perfection) in the next.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:26101:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <div n="1" type="meditation">
               <pb facs="tcp:26101:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:26101:17"/>
               <head>THE FIRST MEDITATION <hi>VVhat loue Chriſte ſhewed at his laſt ſupper.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE Sonne of God Chriſte Ieſus God &amp; man in the whole decourſe of his life, neuer ceaſed to giue vs ſignes and tokens of his loue towards mankind. For beſides that he was incarnat, &amp; became man, onlie for man, not for Angells, he was borne for man in tyme of a Virgin-Mother without a
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:26101:18"/>Father, who was borne of his Father, &amp; of the wombe of his diuine ſubſtance without a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from all eternitie,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 2. &amp; 109.</note> and he who feedeth all liuing creatures was fedd and nouriſhed by the ſame Virgin Mother,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 135.</note> was ſwad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by her in poore clowts, who was inueſted with his Fathers glorie, was rocked by her a ſleepe, whoſe diuine eyes are euer open, was circumciſed &amp; woare the badge of a ſinner, who could not ſinne, faſted, praied, preached, and all for the loue of man: hee neuer brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed, neuer walked, neuer tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, neuer wrought miracles or other good workes, but for mans example &amp; redemption. But as S.
<note place="margin">Ep. Io 3.</note> Iohn teſtifieth <hi>(and his testimonie is true) vnto the end,</hi> and in the end of his life,
<note place="margin">Ioan. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>he loued vs,</hi> and gaue the greateſt
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:26101:18"/>ſignes of loue that euer he gaue. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
               </p>
               <p>Loue is ſhewed in twoe thinges eſpeciallie, to wit in giuing and ſuffering. For if you preſent one with ſome rich dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant or other pretious thing, you ſhall thereby ſhewe your great loue vnto him, loue ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing it ſelf by guifts, as fire doth by ſparcles, and if you giue him nothing yet do ſuffer much for him, ether in your goods or bodie, you do no leſſe ſhewe your loue to him, yea ſomuch the more, by how much it is har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to ſuffer then to giue. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
               </p>
               <p>Our Bleſſed Sauiour the true louer of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> kind at his laſt ſupper, which was the twye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light of his da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, and the eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of his life, gaue vnto man the greateſt guift which heauen and earth could ſhewe, and which was more worth then a
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:26101:19"/>thowſand heauens and earthes, to wit his ſacred bodie &amp; bloud and euen himſelf God and man in the Bleſſed Sacrament. And although he then ſuffered not death reallie for vs, yet he did ſoone after, and euen then, in that in the Bleſſed Sacrament he repreſented his bodie onlie vnder the ſhapes of bread, and his blood onlie vnder the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes of wine, and ſo apart, he was immolated and ſacrificed for vs myſticallie, and dyed for vs in repreſentation before he died in veritie: and ſoe as ſome Saints to ſhew their deſire to dye, and to prepare themſelues the better to death, haue put on a winding ſheete, or haue en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into their Tombe or mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nument before their death, Soe Chriſt Ieſus in the Bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, and at his laſt ſupper,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:26101:19"/>to ſhew the great deſire he had to dye reallie for vs, did as it were put on the winding ſheete of the ſhapes of bread and wine and wrapped himſelf in them, and ſo died in figure and my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie for vs, before he died in ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, and by this figuratiue and myſticall death prepared him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to a reall death which ſoone after, that is the next daie, he ſuffered for vs, and ſoe in the end of his life he ſhewed his great loue vnto vs both by gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing and ſuffering. But as he firſt ſhewed his loue by giuing himſelf in the Bleſſed Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and by immolating him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in it myſticallie onlie, and in repreſentation; ſo let vs firſt imploy our beſt thoughtes and meditations vpon the Bleſſed Sacrament, and Chriſt his laſt ſupper, in which for a louing
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:26101:20"/>farewell he beſtowed vpon his diſciples the moſt precious ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet that euer was ſeene on earth, conſiſting of no leſſe then his ſacred body &amp; bloud, ſeaſoned and ſauced with the diuinitie it ſelfe: And heere af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, in an other litle treatiſe we ſhal contemplate what he ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for vs in his ſacred Paſſion.</p>
               <p>This Sonne of God and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer of mankind ſhewed great loue vnto vs, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> in that by Incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation and hypoſtaticall &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall vnion of our nature with his diuine perſon, he beſtowed his diuine nature on it, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore S.
<note place="margin">Ioan. 3.</note> Iohn expreſſeth this his loue with a <hi>Sic</hi> or <hi>ſoe,</hi> ſaying: <hi>So God loued the world, that he gaue his onlie begotten Sonne;</hi> and yet thus he beſtowed not his diuine perſon on euerie one in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, but onlie on that nature
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:26101:20"/>particularlie which he tooke of the Virgin-Mothers wombe, &amp; by it on mankind in generall: But in the Bleſſed Sacrament hee imparteth himſelf to euerie one of vs in particular by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, by which he giueth vs his bodie, bloud, ſoule, and diuinitie and ſo <hi>at the end of his life,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioan. 13.</note> and at his laſt ſupper he eſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peciallie <hi>loued vs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O my ſoule ſeing that thy God and louing ſpouſe Chriſt Ieſus hath giuen himſelf, ſoule, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> body, bloud and diuinitie vnto thee, what ſhouldſt thou ſeeke for any other thing? why ſhouldſt thou loue any other thing then him, or for him? He is thine in this Bleſſed Sacrament, thy poſſeſſion thy inheritance and richeſſe:
<note place="margin">Pſal. 143.</note> O thou thrice happie and infinitlie rich, <hi>cuius Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Deus tuus, whoſe God is thy
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:26101:21"/>Lord:</hi> O my ſoule thy ſpouſe ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to content himſelf with thee, content thy ſelf with him: If he can not content thee, <hi>in whom be all the treaſures of wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and knowledge,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Col. 2.</note> in whom is all perfection, beautie and goodnes, nothing will content thee. Noe, ſay vnto him. <hi>Quid mihi eſt in coelo,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 72.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp; a te quid volui ſuper terram? what is to me in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen? and beſides thee what would I vpon the earth?</hi> my heart is ſo ample &amp; capable, that as it can not, ſo neither deſireth it to be enriched but by tuee? If I haue thee, as in the B. Sacrament I haue, I ame rich enough, and without thee I ame poore and miſerable, though I had all but thee: If I haue thee I haue all, and if I haue not thee, though I had all elſe which is in heauen and earth I eſteeme myſelf to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:26101:21"/>haue nothing. Thou o my Lord art <hi>my parte,</hi> my All, let me de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire nothing but thee,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 75.</note> let me loue nothing but thee, or for thee, and as thow haſt loued me all thy life time, but eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciallie <hi>at the end,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Io. 13.</note> and period of thy life, in beſtowing this B. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament on me: ſo giue me the grace by which I may loue thee all the time of my life, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciallie at the end of it, that then eſpeciallie I may quite with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw my loue from the world, and all it can afford, and then giue it onlie to thee, <hi>who at the end</hi> of thy life, in this B. Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment haſt ſo kindlie loued me, that I may dye louing thee, and ſo ceaſing to liue, may neuer ceaſe to loue, becauſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though faith &amp; Hope dye with vs (ſaiths obſcuritie yeelding to the light of glorie, and Hope
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:26101:22"/>not conſiſting with the poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of that we hoped for) yet <hi>Charitie neuer falleth away,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 12.</note> or fayleth, and therefore if I die with it, I ſhall liue with it eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nallie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="meditation">
               <head>THE II. MEDITATION <hi>VVhat Charitie and humilitie Chriſte shewed before he ſatte down to his laſt ſupper.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>OVR B. Sauiour hauing ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten with his diſciples the Paſchall lambe, and vſed allſo the ceremonies preſcribed for the eating of it, ſo to ſhew him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe an obedient obſeruer and ful filler of the old lawe: he ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:26101:22"/>from that Typicall Feaſt of the Paſchall Lambe, &amp; murteth them to the eating of the true lambe of God (to witt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe) <hi>who taketh a way the ſinnes of the world:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Io. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> who was the veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of that figure, a feaſt as farre ſurpaſſing that feaſt of the iewes, as the veritie excelleth the figure, the bodie the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowe. And before he ſitteth downe to this Heauenlie Feaſt, behold what preparation he maketh, what ceremonies he vſeth, to ſhew his diſciples with what reuerence and humilitie, with what loue and charitie, they and all Chriſtians ſhould approch vnto this feaſt.</p>
               <p>Thus S. Iohn deſcribeth it: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
                  <hi>And when ſupper was done &amp;c.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Io. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>he riſeth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſupper</hi> (to witt of the Paſchal Lambe) <hi>and laieth aſide his garments, and hauing taken a
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:26101:23"/>Towell, girded himſelfe, after that he putt water into a baſon, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gane to wash the feete of the diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and to wipe them with the towel, wherewith he was girded.</hi> He laied aſide his vpper gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that he may with more conuenience waſh his diſciples feete, as allſo to ſignifie that in this humble act he laieth aſide in outward apparance his veſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of glorie, to wit the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, ſplendour and light of his diuinitie, and guirdeth himſelf with a towell, to ſignifie that he inueſted himſelf in the towel of our humaine nature, that by it he might wipe aware al the filth and ordure of our ſinnes, and thus prepared he kneeleth downe to waſh his diſciples feete.</p>
               <p>Behold, o my ſoule, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> a rare ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of humilitie, and if thow
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:26101:23"/>conſider it well thou cauſt not but ſtand amazed at it. Behold God kneeling at his creatures feete, waſhing &amp; wiping them. Behold what preparation to this ſacred Feaſte he maketh, what a ceremonie he vſeth, to ſhew to his diſciples with what reuerence and humilitie, with what loue and charitie, with what puritie they and all chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians ſhould approach to this dread Sacrifice, to this Holy Sacrament, which then he was to inſtitute, to diſtribute vnto them, and to offer to his father for them. O ſweete Ieſus, how doſt thou humiliate, and euen debaſe thy ſelfe, to controle our pride, and to ſet vs an example of humilitie euer to be vſed, and eſpeciallie when we come to this holy Sacrament and dread Sacrifice.</p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:26101:24"/>
               <p>Abraham waſhed the feete of three Pilgrims, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 18.</note> or at leaſt fetched water for them to waſh, whom after, he found to be An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, but they were but Angels and he but a Patriarch; Chriſte is the God of Patriarchs whom Abraham ſerued, &amp; he waſhed not Angels feete but poore fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhermens feete, whoſe Lord &amp; Maſter, whoſe God and Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour he was.
<note place="margin">Luc. 7.</note> Marie Magdalen waſhed Chriſts feete with her teares and wiped them with her haires: but Chriſt was her God, and ſhe a ſinner who had offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and ſo there was more hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie in Chriſt in permitting her to waſh and wipe his feete, then in her in waſhing and wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping them: But thou O Sauiour of the world, God and man waſhedſt the feete of thy crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and euen of fiſhermen
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:26101:24"/>which are commonlie fowle, &amp; euen of Iudas who had betraied thee,
<note place="margin">Math. 26.</note> and euen then had ſold thee to the Iewes.</p>
               <p>But O Peeter, for to thee he offereth firſt this ſeruice, wilt thou permit thy ſo louing ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, thy God and Creatour to waſh thy feete? wilt thou ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept this honour to be done to thee, with ſo much diſhonour redounding vnto him? No ſaith he:
<note place="margin">Io. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>thou shalt not wash my feete for euer,</hi> yet Chriſte threatneth Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eter, that, <hi>vnles he wash him he shall haue noe parte with him</hi> He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ere Peeter was troubled with co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarie &amp; repugna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t thoughts. To permitte Chriſt to waſh his feete, was much repugnant to the humble conceit he made of himſelf and to the high eſteeme he had of Chriſt, not to permite him was now after a comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:26101:25"/>diſobedience, and after a threatning was loſſe of the heauenlie glorie, for which he had left all, and of which he had ſeene a glimſe in the Trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>figuration of his maſter. I ame loath (ſaith Peeter to himſelf) to ſuffer my Lord God ſo to debaſe himſelf as to waſh my feete, I ame loath allſo to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſobey him who hath ſoueraigne authoritie, but rather then I will be diſobedient to ſuch a Lord and maſter, or looſe my parte with him, that is the bliſſe of heauen, for which I haue left my nettes and hooks, and al I hadd, <hi>wash O Lord</hi> (ſaith he) ſince thou wilt haue it ſo, <hi>not onlie my feete, but my hands allſo and head:</hi> A contemplatiue ſoule will heere take delight to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the holie contention be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuixt the maſters &amp; the ſeruants
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:26101:25"/>humilitie. But the humilitie of the Maſter, as being the greater, in the ende ouercommeth, and ſo the maſter and God &amp; man, kneeling at Peeters feete, wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth them and wipeth them, &amp; peraduentur kiſſeth them. And hauing done this humble office to Peeter, he doth the ſame to the reſt of the diſciples, &amp; euen to the traitour Iudas.</p>
               <p>O yee Angels who ſerue this your God, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> and attend and waite on him in Heauen with all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence, behold your Lord and God,
<note place="margin">Eſa. 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Philip. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>to whom euerie knee of the celeſtials terreſtrials, and Infernals boweth:</hi> kneeling at the feete of fiſhermen, girded with a towel, waſhing and wiping their fowle feete, o humilitie, and waſhing &amp; wiping Iudas his feete, who had traiterouſlie ſold him for thirtie pence, o Charitie. O yee
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:26101:26"/>heauenlie Spirits, you deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded at this your Maſters nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitie, admiring to ſee the Sonne of glorie borne in a ſtable, layed in a manger: but then he was worſhipped by the ſhepheardes: then great troups of you did ſing your Chriſtmas Carolle of <hi>Gloria in Altiſsimis Deo,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luc. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>glorie in the higheſt to God:</hi> and then an vnwonted ſtarre ſhined at this ſolemnitie, and ſoone after that, three Kings came fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Eaſt to adore him &amp; preſent him on theire knees with kinglie guifts: but if you deſcende now, you ſhall ſee him honoured of none, but honouring his owne vaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſals, and debaſing himſelf ſo farre, as to waſh and to wipe their feete. O yee courtiers of the King and court of Heauen, ſhew your ſelues courteours, &amp; permitte not your King thus to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:26101:26"/>be vilified: but rather do you (who in that you are Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teours know well what cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies are moſt conuenient) performe this humble office for your Maſter, do you waſh his diſciples feete, and his in the firſt place, he being your and their kinge: O yee Heauens &amp; celeſtiall globes and ſtar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, who haue the higheſt place in this world, with what manners can you keepe your ſo high &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent places, ſeing your Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour kneeling to his creatures, God, to man. O thou Sunne &amp; Prince of the Planets, the lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe and eye of the world, who il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luminateſt the celeſtiall &amp; ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſtriall world, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt thou endure to ſee thy Sunne of whome thow borroweſt thy light, in this poſture? Deſcend rather and humiliat thy ſelfe with thy
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:26101:27"/>Creatour, or elſe withdrawe thy light and thy ſight from ſuch a ſpectacle. Ioſeph the Patriarch ſaw the ſunne and moone and ſtarrs adoring him,
<note place="margin">Gen. 34.</note> but this he ſaw done onlie in a dreame and viſion, but behold now, not the Sunne and moone adoring our true Ioſeth Ieſus Chriſt, but himſelf adoring, that is knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to his creatures and diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples.</p>
               <p>O humble God, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> it is the dutie of all creatures euen Angels to adore thee who art their crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour, how then hoppeneth it that thou in a manner adoreſt thy diſciples, that is kneeleſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them? But he anſwereth <hi>ſine modo,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>ſic enim decet nos implere omnem iuſtitiam: ſuffer me,</hi> thus to humble myſelf for this time, <hi>for ſo it becommeth vs to fullfill all iuſtice.</hi> It is conuenient that the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:26101:27"/>creatour ſhould thus humble himſelfe euen to the earth, that his creatures maie be exalted, to heauen: It is conuenient that he thus ſhould humble himſelf to teach his diſciples, and in them all chriſtians to humble them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, not onlie to their betters and ſuperiours, but alſo to their ſubiects and Inferiours; to giue them to vnderſtand by this humble waſhing and wiping his diſciples fowle feete, that it is hee who by his bloud waſheth all ſinfull ſoules from the filth and ordure of their ſinnes.</p>
               <p>VVho is able to explicate, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ay to conceaue the lownes of this humilities? certes no mortal creature: for all though we may ſee the earth on which Chriſte kneeleth, &amp; to which he is deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended, yet from how high he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s thus fallen, none can tall but
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:26101:28"/>the Saints and Angels, who ſee clearlie the hight of his diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, and ſo none but they can ſee the lownes of this humilitie Nor can they ſee it perfectlie: onlie God himſelf can, who on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie can comprehend his owne hight &amp; tallnes, which is infini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te. To know how lowea val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie is, you muſt know how high the mountaine is, &amp; ſo to know the vallie of this our Sauiours humilitie, you muſt know how high the mountaine of his diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie is, which none but God can perfectlie know, becauſe he onlie comprehendeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe and his owne hight and tallnes. But as there was neuer humilitie ſo low as this, ſo was there humilitie neuer ſo exalted as this. The higher in dignitie the perſon is who humbleth himſelf, the lower is his humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:26101:28"/>becauſe his falle &amp; deſcent is ſo, much the lower, by how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much his dignitie is higher, and the higher the perſon is who humbleth himſelfe, the more his humllitie is exalted and ino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, as the lower in dignitie &amp; baſer the perſon is, the leſſe gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce hath his humilitie, and ſo hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie is graced by the dignitie of the perſon, and graceth allſo the perſon, and humilitie is the honour of honour, and honour is the honour of humilitie. And conſequentlie this humilitie of Chriſt, God and man, was the loweſt that euer was, and yet the higheſt.</p>
               <p>O my ſoule, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> learne of this thy God, humilitie: he the Creatour thought not much to humble himſelf to the diſciples his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and in this to thee who allſo art his creature, and wilt
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:26101:29"/>thou thinke much to ſtoupe to him the Creatour? He ſo noble and ſo high in dignitie hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled himſelfe, and thou (who though thou wert a King) art baſe in reſpect of him, wilt thou diſdaine humilitie? he humbled himſelf to his ſubiects and Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours, wilt thou thinke ſcorne to humiliate thy ſelfe to thy equales, yea to thy ſuperiours? He vouchſafed to waſh his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples fowle feete, thou thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt ſcorne to do any baſe of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, though none is baſe which humilitie graceth, and yet thou art a creature, hee thy Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour. O my ſoule by this thy Sauiours humble ceremonie of waſhing the diſciples feete be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he admitted them to the B. Sacrament, learne to rinſe and waſhe thy ſelf cleane from all filth of ſinne in the Sacrament
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:26101:29"/>and lauatorie of Pennance, before thou approach to the <hi>holie of holies,</hi> and the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maculate lambe of God con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined in this bleſſed Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, learne by this humilitie of Chriſte which he vſed im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatlie before the inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and diſtribution of this Sacred Sacrament, with what reuerence and feare thou ſhouldſt approach vnto it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering thy Indignitie, and with what humilitie allſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering thy baſenes and it's dignitie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="meditation">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:26101:30"/>
               <head>THE III. MEDITATION <hi>How bountifull a feast maker and Oſte Christ shewed himſelfe and how grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> a feaſt he exhibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to his diſciples in the B. Sacrament.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THIS ſweete Sauiour after the feaſt of the Paſchall Lambe, hauing waſhed &amp; wiped his diſciples feete, to prepare them to the feaſte of his ſacred bodie and bloud, the veritie of that figure, he ſitteth down and inuiteth his diſciples and euen Iudas to ſitte downe with him, and euerie one being placed,
<pb facs="tcp:26101:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26101:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:26101:31"/>and expecting what feaſt he would beſtowe on them at his farewell, which was then at hand, he taketh bread into his hands, ſaying vnto them,
<note place="margin">Mar. 14. Luc. 22.1. Cor. 11.</note> take ye and eate, <hi>this is my bodie,</hi> and leaſt they ſhould thinke that he gaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> but a figure of his bodie as he did when he gaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Paſchall Lambe, he not onlie calleth it in plaine tearmes but addeth as S. Luke relateth <hi>his bodie which is giuen for you,</hi> as S. Paule telleth vs, <hi>which shall be deliuered for you:</hi> to witt on the Croſſe. And leaſt they might <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>magin that he gaue them onlie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> figure of his bloud, he not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ie ſtileth it in plaine tearmes is blood, but addeth as S. Mathew and S. Marck relate <hi>which shall be shed ſor many;</hi> as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Luke writeth, <hi>which shall be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>dd for you:</hi> And ſeing that
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:26101:32"/>breade, or a bare figure of Chriſts bodie (ſuch as was <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> and the Paſchall lambe) was not deliuered, or crucified for vs, but onlie Chriſte his true bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, nor wine, or a bare figure of Chriſtes bloud was ſhed for vs, but onlie his true bloud, it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth that Chriſt at his laſt ſupper gaue to his diſciples his true bodie and bloud, becauſe h gaue that bodie <hi>which was deliured for vs</hi> on the Croſſe, and he gaue them to drinke of that bloud <hi>which was shed for them</hi> on the Croſſe; And foraſmuch as his diuinitie was ſo inſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rablie vnited both to his bodie and ſoule, that death which ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated them one from the other, could not ſeparate them from the diuinitie, it followeth alſo that Chriſte then gaue to his diſciples his bodie, ſoule,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:26101:32"/>bloud and diuinitie, all being vnited in him.</p>
               <p>ô bountifull feaſtmaker, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> ô precious and coſtlie feaſt:
<note place="margin">Pſal. 8.</note> ô Lord what is man that thou ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>udſt ſo much eſteeme of him as to beſtow on him thy ſacred bodie &amp; bloud ſanctified by the diuinitie, yea thy owne ſelfe no leſſe then God and man? ô li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berall Oſte who entertaineſt thy gueſts with ſo precious a banquet, and yet demaundeſt nothing for their ordinarie.
<note place="margin">Heſter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 1.</note> No Aſſueru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> euer made ſuch a feaſt as this, whether wee reſpect the Oſte yea and kinge that hath made it, to wit Chriſt Ieſus, God and man King of Heauen and earth, or the gueſts who are inuited, to wit his Appoſtles, and their ſucceſtours, yea all Chriſtians euen Kings and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours: or the feaſt it ſelfe
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:26101:33"/>which is the holie fleſh &amp; bloud of Chriſt ſeaſoned with the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinitie, more worth then hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and earth, yea then a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand worlds, or the coſt at which the feaſt maker was in preparing this feaſt, for it coſt him his death &amp; paſſion, which was the price of our Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and was ſuffieient to haue redeemed a thouſand worlds; or the continuance of the feaſte which began at Chriſt his laſt ſupper, continueth to this day, and ſhall continue to the worlds end: for as <hi>Manna</hi> rained continuallie from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to feede the Iewes in the deſert and neuer was wanting till they came to the land of promiſe, ſo as long as we liue in the deſert of this life, this our <hi>Manna,</hi> of which that was but a ſhadow and figure, ſhall rayne
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:26101:33"/>vpon Catholicke Chriſtians, by the conſecratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Prieſt til we come to Heauen our true land of Promiſe, where in ſteed of Chriſts bodie and bloud, which now wee eate &amp; drinke by communion, we ſhall feede of the diuinitie it ſelfe by cleare viſion &amp; fruition. O my ſoule, how hard hearted art thou, if this great benefit, this Roiall &amp; coſtlie feaſte, do not melt thee into loue, and reſolue thee into gratitude.</p>
               <p>O feaſt of feaſts, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> noe Epicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſme but Chriſtianiſme, no gluttonie or drunkenneſſe, to eate and drinke often at this feaſt, but temperance, ſobrietie, pietie, Religion. Of this feaſt onlie ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be auerred thoſe words of Eccleſiaſtes.
<note place="margin">Eccl. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>Laudaui igitur letitiam, quod non eſſet bonum ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſub ſole, niſi quod comederet
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:26101:34"/>&amp; biberet: I therefore haue prayſed mirth, that there was no good thing for a man vnder the ſunne, but that he should eate and drinke and be glad:</hi> to wit in this feaſt of the B. Sacrament.</p>
               <p>ô happie wee, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> who are ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h honoured, as to ſit at this Table; where the Angels waite and attende, and we ſit downe at the table, and are feaſted with ſuch coſtlie &amp; pretious meates, who are no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> worthie the crum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes that fall from this table. ô happie we, who being fedde with this Princelie and Kinglie fare, are fatted therewith, and therby inobled &amp; made kings. Becauſe as Iacob ſaid of the bread of Aſer<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſo we may much more ſay of this bread;
<note place="margin">Gen. 49.</note> 
                  <hi>Pinguis eſt panis Chriſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> &amp; praebebit delicias Regibus: The bread of Chriſte is fatte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and shall giue dainties to kinges:</hi>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:26101:34"/>Either becauſe in that it is eaten by vs, it maketh vs Kings, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is meate onlie for Kings, and is not to be geuen to any but thoſe who are Kings and Lords, domineering ouer their owne ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſualities, and paſſions, yea ouer the world, fleſh and deuill. O happie wee who eating in this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Sacrament Chriſtes ſacred bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die and drinking his bloud, are made generous and noble, as he is, yea, in a proportio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, diuine as he is, Gods by participation, as he is God by eſſence, yea of his bloud, kinred and linage. Happie wee who eating Chriſts bodie &amp; drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king his bloud are not onlie <hi>Chriſtiani</hi> Chriſtians, but allſo <hi>Chriſtiferi</hi> bearers of Chriſte,
<note place="margin">Cyril'us H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eroſ. Catech. 4. myſt.</note> yea <hi>Deiferi,</hi> bearers of God, and lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s of him within vs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="meditation">
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:26101:35"/>
               <head>THE FOVRTH MEDITATION <hi>How prouident a</hi> Paterfamilias <hi>and good man of the howſe of our ſoule and the Church, Chriſte is by this B. Sacrament.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ALmightie God out of his infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite goodnes &amp; bountie, hath ſhewed himſelfe in this B. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, to be a moſte wiſe and prouident, and liberall <hi>Paterfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milias</hi> or howſekeeper, hauing laied vp in ſtore ſuch prouiſion for the Howſe of his Church, and for euerie one of vs in particular. He is a howſekceper moſt proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent
<pb facs="tcp:26101:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26101:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:26101:36"/>in reſpect of all liuing crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. The whole worlde is his howſe, all liuing Creatures his familie, for euerie one of which he prouideth meate and drinke according to euerie ones nature. Plants and hearbes he feedeth with moyſture, which by their rootes as by mouthes, they drawe from the earth, beaſtes with plants, hearbes, corne, and graſſe: Fiſhes with water and other foode which they findc in the water, &amp; mens bodies he fedeth with fleſh, fiſhe. hearbes and fruites of the earthe, and therefore Dauid ſaith that it is God:
<note place="margin">Pſ. 146.</note> 
                  <hi>Qui dat iumentis eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cam ipſorum, &amp; pullis coruorum inuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantibus eum, who giues to beasts their foode, and to the yong rauens that call vpon him.</hi> He ſpecifieth yong rauens, partlie to ſignifie that God hath care of all his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures euen the vileſt, partlie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:26101:37"/>as S.
<note place="margin">Serm. de. He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia.</note> Chriſoſtome auerreth the old crowes do often tymes neglect their young ones (as when they ſuſpect them not to be their owne broode) and then God is the nurſe of the young ones, fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding them with flies, or the thicke ayre or ſuch like.</p>
               <p>But more bountifullie, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> &amp; care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullie God Almightie prouideth for man, and feedeth him in bodie with the beſt meates, and in ſoule with learning and vertue, and aboue all; this great howſekeeper hath euer and cheeflie prouided for his Church, though not alwaies in the ſame manner. For otherwiſe did he prouide for it before Chriſts comming, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe after his cumming, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe for the Iewes, otherwiſe for the Chriſtians: For the Iewes being children in ſpirituall life who liued vnder the Pedagogue
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:26101:37"/>of the lawe, which brought no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to <hi>perfection,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 4.</note> and could not giue them full-groughe, nor make them men, they were to be fedde like children with the light mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of the figuratiue Sacrificies &amp; Sacraments of the old lawe:
<note place="margin">Heb. 5.</note> And therefor S. Paule ſaith that <hi>they had need of milke, and not of strong meat, but strong meat is for the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect,</hi> that is Chriſtians, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are perfect men in a ſpirituall life, are not to be fed with light figures, but with the ſolid verities of thoſe figures. They were fedde with <hi>Manna</hi> and the Paſchall lamb, we who are Chriſtians, are fedde with the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred body and bloud of Chriſte which are ſolid verities of thoſe figures, and meat for the ſtrong and perfect, not for weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings and children, as the Iewes were.</p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:26101:38"/>
               <p>Ioſeph the Patriarch, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> as we reade in Geneſis, whoe was as the <hi>Paterfamilias</hi> of Pharao his houſe yea and of all Egipt,
<note place="margin">Gen. 43.</note> and who in a dearth of ſeauen yeares, proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded them of corne aboundantlie; when his brethren reſorted allſo vnto him for corn, he inuited them to a feaſt, and gaue to euerie one of them his portion, but to Beniamin his yongeſt brother, he gaue a portion fiue times bigger then was the portion which he gaue to his elder brethren. Euen ſoe our Ioſeph Chriſt Ieſus; who furniſhed not Egipt with corne, as Ioſeph did, but the whole Church of God with the ſacred Euchariſte,
<note place="margin">Io. 6.</note> which the Prophet calleth,
<note place="margin">Zach. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>frumentum electorum, the wheate of the elect:</hi> and <hi>wine ſpin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging virgins:</hi> gaue thereby to the Chriſtinns the younger brother in regarde of time, a portion of the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:26101:38"/>B. Sacrament, which is greater &amp; more precious, not by fiue times onlie, but by fiue thouſand times then was the portion of <hi>Manna,</hi> or the Paſchall lambe, or all thoſe Sacrifices and Sacraments which he gaue to the Iewe the elder brother.</p>
               <p>O liberall &amp; magnificent houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keeper, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> whoe haſt made ſo great and ſo Roiall prouiſion for thy familie, the Church. VVhen I conſider the aboundance of corn, graſſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> hearbes, fruits, which God hath prouided for the ſuſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of all liuing creatures, euen the litle ſparowes, and yong ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens, I ſtand as a man amazed, &amp; Iſaie vnto myſelf; out of what granarie or ſtore howſe, or Barne commeth all this prouiſion? But when I behold the aboundance of the <hi>wheate of the Elect,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Zach. 9.10.6.</note> &amp; of the <hi>bread of life,</hi> of which <hi>whoeſoeuer
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:26101:39"/>eateth liueth for euer,</hi> VVhich our B. Sauiour God and man, hath prouided for vs in this B. Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, I ceaſe to admire there, &amp; can neuer ceaſe to admire heere, and I ſaie vnto my ſelfe: Out of what granarie commeth this <hi>wheate of the Elect,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Zaca. 8.10.6.</note> out of what pa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie cometh this <hi>bread of life,</hi> which feedeth our ſoules and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth them ſpirituall nouriſhment, and life of grace? of which we feede dailie, and yet the bread is neuer conſumed, neuer dimini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed. VVhen I conſider the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rietie of fountaines, ſpringes, wells, and riuers, which our Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed God hath prouided for men and beaſtes to drinke on, I ſtande amazed, and I ſaie to my ſelfe: out of what brewhowſe cometh all this drinke? who is the Butler that continuallie draweth it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> but when I Behold the wine
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:26101:39"/>which <hi>ſpringeth Virgins,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Zac. 9.</note> &amp; which is drunk dailie &amp; by many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands in this B. Sacrament: I ſtand amazed heere and I ceaſe to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire there, and ſaie to my ſelfe, out of what celler commeth this wine? who draweth it? who filleth it out? And which maketh me more to admire, I ſee many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands doe drinke dailie of this wine, and yet the Celler is neuer emptied, the wine neuer dimini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed. O bountifull and prouident howſekeeper (ſweete Ieſus) who prouideſt ſuch meate and drinke as neuer conſumeth: for I ſee that:
<q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Sumit vnus, ſumunt mille</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Quantum iſti tantum ille</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Nec ſumptus conſumitur.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>One takes it and a thouſand may</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>As much as hee ſoe much doe they</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Nor is it conſumed att all.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>VVhen I call to minde, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> ô Lord, how once thow fedſt in the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:26101:40"/>deſert, the Iſraelits with Quailes and <hi>Manna</hi> from Heauen and ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt them water to drink out of a hard rock,
<note place="margin">Excodi. 16. &amp; 17.</note> I ame aſtoniſhed: But when I conſider with what an heauenlie <hi>Manna,</hi> made not in the aire by the fingers, of Angels, as that <hi>Manna</hi> was, but by the fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gars of the Holy Ghoſt in the Heauen of the B. Virgins wom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be, thou feedeſt vs in the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Sacrament, during our aboade in the deſert of this life, &amp; wilt feed vs till we come to our land of promiſe; I ceaſe to wonder there, and I onlie wonder heere.</p>
               <p>VVhen I call to minde how thou, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 14.</note> o Bleſſed Sauiour, the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of all thoſe former miracles, didſt feed with fiue barlie loaues &amp; two fiſhes, fiue thouſand men, beſides woemen and children, &amp; ganeſt to euerie one his fille, and yet after that all the guetſts had
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:26101:40"/>eaten aſmuch as ſatisfied them, the leauings and fragments filled twelue boskets, and ſo was grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then the feaſt was at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning; I wonder: But when I conſider how in this B. Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, thou, ô Lord, feedeſt with a farre leſſer quantitie, ſo many millious of Chriſtians ſince thy laſt ſupper, and ſhalt feede them to the ende of the world, and yet the feaſt neuer diminiſheth, but is as great now as it was at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, I ceaſe to wonder there, and I ſtand alltogether amazed heere.</p>
               <p>Behold my ſoule what a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uident and bountifull howſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keeper thy Lord Ieſus is. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> O the happines of Catholikes who haue ſuch aboundance of bread and wine alwaies prepared for them: and ô the miſerie of the Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke, who hauing,
<note place="margin">I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ac. 15.</note> like the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digall
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:26101:41"/>ſonne, left the Church, his heauenlie fathers howſe, is fed onlie with the husks and chaffe of figures, but hath not the ſolid corne to feede on. Lett him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to the Church his Fathers howſe, lett him returne againe &amp; crye with the Prodigall ſonne. <hi>How many of my Fathers hirelings haue aboundance of bread,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luc. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>and I heere perish for famin? I will ariſe, and goe to my Father, and ſaie to him, father I haue ſinned againſt heauen and before thee: I ame not worthie to be called thy ſonne, make me one of thy hire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings.</hi> VVhich if the Hereticke doth, God will admitte him to the heauenlie prouiſion in the B. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament: he will make him par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker,
<note place="margin">Io 6. Zac. 9.</note> of the <hi>bread of life,</hi> and <hi>wine that ſpringeth Virgins,</hi> of which who eateth and drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth ſhall neuer be hungrie or thirſtie again.</p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:26101:41"/>
               <p>This ſacred bread which our <hi>Paterfamilias</hi> hath prepared for his howſehold, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> was kned by the fingers of the Holy Ghoſt, baked in the ſacred ouen of the B. Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins wombe, not by the heate or fire of concupiſcence, but of the Holy Ghoſt, drawne out of the ouen in Chriſt his natiuitie, ſet at the table at Chriſtes laſt ſupper, and euerie daie vpon the Altar, for the nouriſhement of our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenlie fathers howſehold. The wine which all of this howſehold do drinke is moſt pretious,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 22.</note> 
                  <hi>A cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice inebriating:</hi> which inebriateth ſpirituallie, and maketh vs ſleepe to the world: The vine from which this ſacred wine origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nallie procedeth, is Chriſte Ieſus, who called hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelfe <hi>a vine,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Io. 15.</note> ſayinſt to his diſciples <hi>I ame the vine: you the branches,</hi> which vine was plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the vinyard of the B. Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:26101:42"/>wombe, when God the ſonne tooke fleſh of her, the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe of this vine was Chriſtes bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bie preſſed on the croſſe, the wine was his ſacred bloud giuen to the Apoſtles at the laſt ſupper before the preſſing on the Croſſe, but is giuen in the B. Saerament to their ſucceſſours aftet the preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing. By the force which this bread of life giueth, we walke with <hi>Helias,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">3. Reg. 19.</note> not to the mount <hi>Horeb</hi> but to the mount of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and by this ſacred fare we ouercome all difficulties, which either the deuill or the worlde, or our owne fleſh doe laye in our wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e. By this wine the Apoſtles, diſciples and martyrs of the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitiue Church being ſpirituallie drunke, encouraged, and infla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, could not be daunted with all the inſtruments of crueltie, with all the torments and death<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:26101:42"/>which the Tyrants could deuiſe, but were readie to ſuffer all tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m, who ſuffered for them, yea to giue their liues for him, who offered his for them on the Croſſe, &amp; in the B. Sacrament gaue his body and bloud to them.</p>
               <p>O my ſoule, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> ſay vnto this thy bountifull oſte and howſekeeper as Dauid ſaied; <hi>Quid retribuam Domino pro omnibus que retribuit mihi? what shall I giue to God</hi> (to this my Ieſus God and man) <hi>for all things, which he hath giuen to me?</hi> I am leſſe then the leaſt of them, what then ſhall I render thee for this benefite of the B. Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in which thou ſo often gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſt thyſelfe, thy bodie, bloud and ſoule, and diuinitie? I can not giue thee enough for the leaſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rumme of this liuing bread of thy ſacred body, for the leaſt drop of this ſacred wine of thy ſacred
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:26101:43"/>bloud, though I ſhould giue all I ame and haue, &amp; though what I ame were as perfect as the moſt perfect Angell, and though what I haue were aſmuch as Heauen and Earth. O Lord be contente that I confeſſe myſelfe to be ouercome by thee a thouſand ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes in curteſies and fauours, be content that I giue thee my All, for I know thou art noe litle contented, when we giue our All, be it neuer ſo litle.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26101:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="meditation">
               <pb facs="tcp:26101:44" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:26101:44"/>
               <head>THE FIFTH MEDITATION <hi>How Chriſt hath shewed himſelfe in this B. Sacrament a Father and more them a Father vnto vs.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>GOd Almightie is our Father by Creation, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> by which he giueth vs our naturall being, which is a participation of his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſubſtance,
<note place="margin">Phil. li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal. Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Confor lib. 1. con. 12.</note> and by the ſame Creation he is a Common Father to all Creatures, eſpeciallie man, and they are (as Philoſaith) in reſpect of God who created them
<pb facs="tcp:26101:45"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:26101:45"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:26101:46"/>bretheren amongſt themſelues and children of one Father, for which cauſe the deuout Saint Francis called them his brethren and Siſters. Yet there is in this a difference betwix man and other creatures, becauſe man is not only a participation of God his ſubſtance as other creatures are, but is allſo an Image of God, in regarde of his intellectual nature, and his vnderſtanding, will and memorie, by which he repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenteth God and reſembleth him, as the Sonne doth the Father: And therefor God when he was to create man, he ſaid not onlie be man made, as he ſaied, <hi>be light made,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>Be a Firmament made, be there lights made,</hi> but he ſaid, <hi>let vs make man to our Image and likenes.</hi> And ſo God euen by creation is in a more perfect manner a Father of man, and man is in a more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:26101:46"/>manner his Sonne, reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling him as the child doth the Father.</p>
               <p>Secondlie God is Mans Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> and in a more perfect &amp; emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent manner by ſanctifieng grace by which man reccaueth from God a ſupernaturall being, and as S. Peeter ſaith,
<note place="margin">2. Pet 1.</note> 
                  <hi>is Conſors diuinae naturae, partaker of the diuine nature</hi> by which he is the adopted childe of God, &amp; he is his adoptiue Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.
<note place="margin">Rom. 5.</note> VVe were borne of our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Parents dead ſpirituallie in ſoule by originall ſinne: but we are regenereted and borne againe ſpirituallie to a ſupernaturall life by the Grace which we receaue in, and by Baptiſme,
<note place="margin">Ion. 3. Ion. 3.4. &amp; 5. Ion. 1. Rom. 8. Gal. 3. &amp; 4.</note> by which God is our Father, the grace of Baptiſme is our regeneration and ſecond natiuitie, by which we are ſaid <hi>to be borne to God</hi> and to be his <hi>children,</hi> he our <hi>Father.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:26101:47"/>
               <p>But although this be true, yet by and in the B. Sacrament of the Altar, Chriſte the Sonne of God, God and Man, ſheweth himſelfe a perfect Father, and more then a Father. A man is ſaid to be Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of his Sonne, becauſe he im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parteth vnto him his owne nature fleſh and bloud, not the ſame in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diuiduall, but another of the ſame Kinde. But our B. Sauiour in this Holie Sacrament imparteth vnto vs his owne nature, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, fleſh, and bloud, of which he himſelfe conſiſteth. And ſo if the Sonne be called fleſh of his Fathers fleſh, bloud of his bloud though he reccaue not from him the ſame fleſh and bloud which he hath, but other fleſh and bloud of the ſame Kinde: much more may Chriſtians by receauing this Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Sacrament, be called fleſh of Chriſt his fleſh, and bloud of his
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:26101:47"/>bloud they receauing the ſelfe ſame fleſh and bloud of which he conſiſteth. And ſo not onlie by Baptiſme but alſo by this B. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament Chriſt is our Father, and more ſubſtantiallie by this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t then, by that becauſe by that we receaue onlie grace, which is onlie a ſupernatural, &amp; accidental participatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God, by this we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue reallie Chriſts owne body and bloud, yea ſoule and diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, and by his and our burning loue, meeting together, our ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancies are (as S. Cyrill of Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andria ſaith) as it were melted, <hi>and vnited as waxe is to waxe.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lib. 4. in Ioan. ca. 17. Chriſ. lib. 61. ad Pop. Antioc.</note> VVe are as S. Chryſoſtome ſaith, <hi>vnum corpus &amp; membra, ex carne cius &amp; ex oſsibus eius, one body and mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of his flesh and of his bones: we are not only by charitie but reipſa in verie deed mingled with his flesh</hi> for he <hi>ſemetipſum nobis immiſcuis
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:26101:48"/>&amp; corpus ſuum in nos contemperauit vt vnum quid efficiamur tanquam corpus capiti coaptatum, ardenter enim amantium hoc eſt: he hath min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled himſelfe to vs, and hath contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered his bodie into vs that we may be one thing, and as one body linked to the head, for this is the propertie of thoſe that loue ardentlie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O my ſoule how gratefull ſhouldſt thou be to ſuch a Father who hath beſtowed on thee his owne ſubſtance in ſo admirable a manner? <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> how ſhoulds thou ſcorne this worlde and all it can afforde? how ſhoulds thou diſdaine to be aſlaue to the world, fleſh and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, thou being ſo noblie deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended of ſo noble a Father, as is Chriſte Ieſus God and man, King of heauen and Earth? Diuers hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Emperours imagined them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to be born of the Gods, and this imagination made them to
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:26101:48"/>diſdaine all baſenes. Doe not thou then ô my ſoule debaſe thy ſelfe, do not degenerate from this dignitie to thy former vilitie and baſenes of life, who art made par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker of Chriſtes body and bloud, and nouriſhed therewith.</p>
               <p>Lette ſinners whoe thinke of noe other heauen then earth, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> nor of any other pleaſure or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light but carnall, content them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues with their hoggiſh fare of wordlie traſhe, and carnall plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures: do thou take thy onlie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in feeding of this <hi>Manna,</hi> which hath all delight, in eating of this bread of life which brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth eternall life with it, and in drinking of this wine of Chriſts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>loud which ſpringeth Virgins, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ebriateth the ſpirit and reioi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eth the hearte; Let worldlings <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ragge of their noble bloud, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>action and noble deſcent, thou
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:26101:49"/>art more noblie deſcended, to wit from Chriſte the Sonne of God, who in this B. Sacrament is thy Father and more then a Father: thou art of a more noble bloud, becauſe by this B. Sacrament thou art fleſh and bloud of Chriſts fleſh &amp; bloud; who was conceaued &amp; born of a Virgin-mother &amp; by no other ſeed then the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="meditation">
               <head>THE SIXT MEDITATION <hi>How Christ hath shewed himſelfe in the B. Sacrament a Mother and more then a Mother.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe loue of a Mother towards her childe is ſo greate, that none can imagin it but mothers
<pb facs="tcp:26101:49" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26101:50" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:26101:50" rendition="simple:additions"/>themſelues: It is greater then the loue of the Father, becauſe the Mother ſuffereth more for it then the Father doth, ſhe bearing it in her womb nine monthes with great paine, bringing it to light with farre greater, ſhe giuing it her milke, ſwadling it, rocking it, carying it in her armes. And ſo as wee loue that beſt which wee gett with moſt difficultie, ſo ſhe loueth the child moſt becauſe ſhe moſt endureth for it in perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the former officies; and her moſt familiaritie with it from i'ts birth, engendreth the greateſt loue and affection: Hence it is that when holy Scripture would expreſſe great loue, it compareth it to the loue of a mother,
<note place="margin">2. Reg. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>As the mother</hi> ſaith Dauid) <hi>loueth her onlie ſonne ſo did I loue thee, Ionathas:</hi> yea God himſelf explicateth his loue to vs by the loue of a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:26101:51"/>as by the greateſt loue, <hi>VVhy</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>can a woeman forget her Infant &amp;c. and if she should forget yet will not I forget thee.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 49. Iſa. 66.</note> And againe: <hi>As if the mother should ſpeake one faire, ſo will I comfort thee.</hi> And yet againe:
<note place="margin">Io. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>A woeman when she tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaileth hath ſorrow, but when she hath brought forth the child, now she remembreth not the anguish for ioye that a man is borne into the world:</hi> and this the great ioy of the mother is grounded on her great loue, and this her great loue on her great ſorrow and paines which ſhe ſuffered, and on her great familiaritie with her child from its birth, If the loue of a mother be ſo tender towards her child, how great muſt we thinke was the loue of Chriſt towards vs in the B. Sacrament, where he hath ſhewed himſelfe a mother and more then a mother?</p>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:26101:51"/>
               <p>The mother by her pappes gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth her childe her milke, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> and ſo nouriſheth it, ſo our B. Sauiour by his ſacred pappe of this B. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, giueth vs to ſucke his owne bloud, and that which (as S.
<note place="margin">Chryl. ſerm. admon. de Euchar in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenijs &amp;c hom. 24 in 1. ad Cor. 11. hom. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>1 in cap. Io. 19.</note> Chriſoſtome affirmeth) iſſued out of his ſacred fide, and with his bloud the milke alſo of his ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying grace, and therewith nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſheth our ſoules. Mothers vſe to chew the meate which they giue to their litle Infants, ſo to make it fit for their eating, &amp; our B. Sauiour in the Firſt in ſtitution of this B. Sacrament, did eate and as it were, chew his owne fleſh, and did drinke to vs all, in a draft of his owne bloud, to make it fitt for our eating and drinking: and as nature in the mother conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth her bloud into milke, and ſo couereth it with the white colour of milke leaſt the childe ſhould
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:26101:52"/>abhorre to take it in the colour of bloud, ſo our B. Sauiour hath couered his Sacred fleſh &amp; bloud, which he giueth vs to eate and drinke, vnder the vſuall colour of bread, &amp; wine, knowing that we would abhorre to eate his fleſh &amp; drinke his bloud in their owne ſhape and forme.</p>
               <p>And to ſhew himſelfe not onlie as a mother, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> but more then a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, he giueth vs to eate of his owne flelſh, &amp; to drinck his owne bloud, which Mothers do not; They giue their milke which aboundeth in them, not their fleſh or bloud. Chriſt ſhed for vs on the croſſe not his ſuperfluous bloud, but euen that bloud which was neceſſarie to keepe life, and this bloud he giueth vs by the dugge, pappe, and teate of this B. Sacrament.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> O mother and more then any
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:26101:52"/>mother, for as S. Chryſoſtome ſaith, mothers do often tymes gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue ouer their children, to be nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by others; but our B. Sauiour to make vs generous as he is, to make vs ſucke with his bloud his diuine conditions, would not, out of his loue, permite this, but he nouriſheth vs (which no mother will doe) with his owne fleſh &amp; bloud.
<note place="margin">Chryſ. hom. 60. ad pop. An t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>och.</note> O loue aboue the loue of Mothers, ô loue aboue the loue of all creatures, proper onlie to God and the louer of mankind.</p>
               <p>VVith what ſpirituall gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dines then, and hunger, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> ſhould we come to this B. Sacrament, to ſucke out of this dugge the bloud of Chriſte and the milke of grace? <hi>Nonne videtis</hi> (ſaith S.
<note place="margin">Hom. 60. ad pop. An tioch.</note> Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome) <hi>quanta promptitudine par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uuli papillas capiunt, &amp; quanto im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petu labia vberibus inſigunt, acceda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nm tanta nos quoque alacritate
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:26101:53"/>ad hanc meuſam: quiuimo cum longe maiori trahamus tanquam infantes lactanei Spiritus gratiam, &amp; vnus ſit nobis dolor hac eſcapriuari:</hi> Do you not ſee with what promptitude and greedines little Infants take their Mothers pappes, with what a violence they faſten their lippes on the pappes? lett vs alſo come with the like alacritie, yea with a farre greater, let vs like ſucking Infants ſuckr the ſpirite of grace, and let it be our onlie greefe to be depriued of this foode.</p>
               <p>O my fweet ſauiour, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> ô my deare Father and Mother (for ſo thow haſt ſhewed thyſelf in this holie Sacrament) be vnto me a Father and Mother, prouide for me all neceſſaries for a fpirituall life, prouide for me an inheritance in the next, for that it pertaineth to Fathers and Mothers to laie vp treaſures for their children.</p>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:26101:53"/>
               <p>O my deare Father and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> beſtow for euer thy loue on me, for that it is naturall for pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents to loue their children, and loue me not for a while but for euer. The more perfect parents are the longer they loue their young ones. The beaſts of the Earthe and the fowles of the ayre, do loue and care and prouide for their young ones, onlie for a time, that is, till they be able to ſhift for themſelues, and after that, they make no diſtinctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> betwixt them and others, but the Father and Mother amongeſt men, becauſe they are more perfect parents, do loue their children euen to death, and prouide an Inheritance for them to liue on after the parents death. God almightie therefore who is our Father not onlie by creation, but alſo by grace and Sanctification, and a moſt perfect
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:26101:54"/>Father alſo, loueth his Elected children for all eternitie, euen be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they were, as he, <hi>loued Iacob before he was borne</hi> and (as Hiere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie ſaith) <hi>in an euerlaſting charitie he loued his choſen people:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 9. Hierm. 22.</note> he loueth them heere by grace, and in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and that eternallie, by eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall glorie.</p>
               <p>VVherefore O my ſweet Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> thow who in this B. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament haſt ſhewed thyſelfe a ſupernaturall and moſt perfect Father, and Mother to all that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue thee in it, and euen to mee though otherwiſe a wretched ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, loue mee I beſeech thee as thy child (for parents do natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallie loue their children) &amp; loue me perpetuallie, heere by thy gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce and in heauen by thy eternall glorie: &amp; if thou ſhouldſt vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe ſo to loue me, I care not though all the world ſhould hate
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:26101:54"/>me, for if thou by thy loue ſtand for me, who can ſtand againſt me? And becauſe by this Holy Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t thou art my Father &amp; Mother giue me grace alwaies to loue thee alſo becauſe children do na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turallie loue their parents, and graunt me grace to loue thee abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue Father and Mother, for that in this B. Sacrament thou art be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come vnto me more then any Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Mother. And if thou loue me how can I miſcarrie, thou protecting whom thou loueſt? And if I loue thee, nothing can come amiſſe vnto mee, be it proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peritie or aduerſitie, health or ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knes, riches or pouertie, becauſe <hi>to them that loue thee all things coope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate vnto good,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ro. ms.</note> and ſo euen my ſinc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes (ô Lord) though they diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour thee, and hurte me for a time, yet if I loue thee, they will turne to thy greater honour, &amp; my
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:26101:55"/>greater ſpirituall profite, becauſe through thy grace they will turne, as were the ſinnes of Marie Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalen to her, motiues to a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter penance, and ſpurrs to a better life then otherwiſe I ſhould haue ledd.</p>
               <p>Thou comawndeſt vs (ô Lord) <hi>to honour our Father and mother,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 20</note> 
                  <hi>that we may be long liuers vpon the Earth.</hi> Euerie effect if it had reaſon would honour it's cauſe, of which it hath it's being, and by which it ſubſiſteth, and ſo the light would honour and loue the Sunne, the riuers their fountaines, the fruites their trees, the yong birds their oldones, the yong beaſtes thoſe that did generate them, if they had reaſon; Man then who is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued with reaſon, muſt honour his Father and Mother, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got him &amp; brought him to light, and after God gaue him his life
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:26101:55"/>and being, and to this he is obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by the Lawe of God and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. How much then, o ſwere Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, ſhould I honour thee who in this B. Sacrament art a Superna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall Father and Mother vnto me, and more then any Father and Mother?</p>
               <p>Thou commaundeſt vs ô Lord to acknowlge no other Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God, ſaieng: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="0"/>
                  <note place="margin">Matt. 23</note> 
                  <hi>call none Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to yourſelf vpon earth for one is your Father, he that is in heauen.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe although our Carnal Fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hers be our true Fathers, yet in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of thee, ô Lord, they are no Fathers, thou by creation being more our Father then they, and by ſanctification, and this B. Sacrament, being our Superna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall Father &amp; more then our car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Father and mother. Our car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall parents are but halfe Fathers and Mothers generating onlie
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:26101:56"/>our bodie, whereas thou art our totall Father, that is of ſoule aſwell as bodie; Giue me grace then ô heauenlie Father to loue and honour thee aboue my carnal Father and Mother, to forſake them rather then offend and fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake thee by ſinne, that ſo ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouring and louing thee, <hi>I may be a long liuer,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 20.</note> not vpon earth, but in heauen wher my life ſhall be eternitie.</p>
               <p>And becauſe children do wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linglie followe their Fathers and Mothers ſtepps, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> and do imitate them in all their actions bee they good or badde, thinking it conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient for them to do what they ſee their parents do before them; giue me, ô Lord, by thy grace a deſire &amp; a delight to imitate thee in all thy holie actions &amp; vertues, in thy humilitie,
<note place="margin">Phil. 2.</note> patience, chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie &amp; <hi>obedience euen vnto death.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:26101:56"/>
               <p>Thou ſaydſt once to the Iewes,
<note place="margin">Io. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>If you be the children of Abraham, do the works of Abraham:</hi> wherefore ſeing that by this Holie Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, thou ô Lord, art my Father &amp; Mother, &amp; they who receaue it worthilie, are thy children, giue me grace to imitate thy vertues and holy actions, lett them be patterns and examples for me to followe, let them be alwayes before my eyes that I may euer behold them, let them be alwaies in my heart, that I may euer loue them, lett them be alwaies in my hands, that I may euer practiſe them, ſo I ſhall be to thee as an obedient child doing in all things thy holie will, and thou wilt be to mee a louing Father, furniſhing me not with a temporall eſtate, as carnall pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents onlie can doe, but proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding for me heere grace, and an inheritance in heauen of glorie,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:26101:57"/>which thou haſt layed vp in ſtore for all eternitie, for thoſe that are thy true and obedient children, fullfilling in all things thy holy will and commandement.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="meditation">
               <head>THE SEAVENTH MEDITATION <hi>VVhat a freind Chriſt hath shewed himſelf in the B. Sacrament.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ARiſtotle the Prince of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers who diued as farre almoſt into the ſecrets of nature as naturall reaſon could permit,
<note place="margin">Eib 2. Lth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>c.</note> thought there could be no per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and proper freindſhip be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuixt God and man, becauſe there could be no equalitie or paritie
<pb facs="tcp:26101:57" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26101:58" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:26101:58"/>betwixt them, God being infinite in Maieſtie, and ſoueraigne and ſupreme in authoritie &amp; digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, man infinitlie beneath him in degree, baſe alſo of condition (though he be an Emperour) in compariſon of God, with which diſparitie he thought familiaritie would not conſiſt, which yet he thought was belonging to freinds and freindſhip.</p>
               <p>VVherein all though he erred yet his errour was excuſable, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe by naturall reaſon he could not diſcouer the Excellencie of Grace, much leſſe of th' Incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the fountaine of all grace. For grace being a ſupernaturall guift of God, eleuateth nature aboue nature, and maketh ſuch a kind of equalitie betwixt man &amp; God that S. Peeter ſaith, we are <hi>conſortes diuinae naturae,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Pet.</note> 
                  <hi>partakers of the diuine nature.</hi> And by Incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:26101:59"/>God became man &amp; man God, and ſo man was conſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiall to God, and equall to him, though not as man, but as God. And ſo God and man by theſe meanes were made freinds: to which honour God out of his goodnes hath exalted vs and hath made vs equal to him by his deſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, &amp; as it were debaling him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſo lowe, as to be man with vs. O the goodnes of God that would not onlie be content but alſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to contract freindſhip with vs his creatures, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> as though God could not be God vnles he were good to vs, or could not liue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentedlie vnles wee were his freinds, and he ours. O my ſoule do thou heere ſtand amazed, and in amazment fay to thy God, who am I that thou ſhoulds ſo eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me of me as to vouchſafe to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of me as thy freind? I am not
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:26101:59"/>worthie ô Lord to be thy vaſſall, and ſlaue, how then doeſt thou take me for thy freind? VVhat Emeprour will ſtoupe ſo low as to be a freind to his vaſſals, and yet man though an Emperour is but thy vaſſall? It is honour ô Lord, to much for me to be ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant to ſuch a Prince, how much more then to much, to be thy freind? Speake Dauid what thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt thou of this honour which God doth to men in accounting them his freinds? <hi>To mee</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>thy freinds are become honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble exceedinglie, nimis honorati,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſa. 38.</note> 
                  <hi>to much honoured.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nay God is not content onlie to be our freind, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> but hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted with vs a firmer freind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and more indiſſoluble, then euer was betwixt man and man. Damon and Pythias. Pylades &amp; Oreſtes and others are famous for
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:26101:60"/>their freindſhip, which was ſo greate that the one eſteemed th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> other another himſelf, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the one was readie to dye for the other: but this freindſhip, ô Lord is, not comparable to thy freindſhip which thou haſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted with man.</p>
               <p>Thou firſt haſt contracted freindſhip betwixt thy ſelf and man by Incarnation, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> by which thou art linked to man, in a moſt admirable vnitie in one perſon, by which God is man and man is God, which freindſhip is ſo faſte firme, and indiſſoluble, that ſo long as, God ſhall be God, he ſhall be man: and man ſhall be God. O my ſoule be thou neuer ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratfull as euer to forget this freindſhip, It is the ground of all other freindſhips, &amp; the moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable. Damon and Pythias were linked onlie in affection, ſo
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:26101:60"/>was lonathas and Dauid,
<note place="margin">1. Reg. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> whoſe ſoule is ſayd to haue been g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ed to Ionathas his ſoule, but by this freindſhip of Incarnation God &amp; man were vnited in one perſon reallie and ſubſtantiallie. O Lord what is man that thou ſhouldſt ſo grace &amp; fauour him, as to Vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to be ſo neerlie linked in freindſhip to him, as to be one per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon with him.</p>
               <p>Secondlie thou haſt linked thy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in freindſhip with man by grace and charitie, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> and this is an effect of the former freindſhip, becauſe the Incarnation is the fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taine of al grace.
<note place="margin">Iac. 2.</note> Abrahamin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dewed with this grace, is called by S. Iames. <hi>Amicus Dei, the freind of God.</hi> And Chriſt ſpeaketh to his Apoſtles in thoſe freindlie and comfurtable words:
<note place="margin">Ioa. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>You are my freinds if you do the things that</hi> I commaund <hi>you, now I call you not
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:26101:61"/>ſeruants, for the ſeruant knoweth not what his Lord doeth, but you I haue called freinds, becauſe all thinges whatſoeuer I heard of my Father I haue notified vnto you.</hi> And all the Iuſt, by this freindſhip are freinds to him, and he to them. This freindſhip once made, on God his part, is neuer diſſolued, for he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ceaſeth to be our freind till we turne his enemies by mortall ſinne. And although by ſinne this freindſhip be to often broken on our part by particular men, yet it is generallie ſo firme, that there was neuer ſo firme a freindſhip be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt man and man, as there is by grace and charitie betwixt God and man.</p>
               <p>There is no greater freindſhip or charitie ſaith our B. Sauiour, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> 
                  <hi>then that a man yeald his life for his freinds</hi> (which few freinds haue done for one another) and yet our
<note place="margin">Io. 15.</note>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:26101:61"/>B. Sauiour hath died not onlie for his frends, but euen for his foes, to make them freinds, and thoſe his freinds haue bene ſo lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing and ſo conſtant to him, that many millions of Chriſtians haue died for him, as appeares in our ſo many Martyrs, whom no threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of Tyrants could ſoe daunt, no promiſes ſo allure, no tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſo terrifie, no deaths ſo ſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, as to make them denie Chriſt or his religion, but ſtrengthened with grace &amp; chatitie, they trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phed ouer all, and for his loue they forſooke all, (as lands, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uings, life) rather then they would forſake him: and as he firſt died for them, ſo did they dye for him. O Lord tye me by this linke of freindſhip vnto thee, that I may preferre thy loue before the loue of all but thee, or for thee, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme me ſo in this freindſhip, that
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:26101:62"/>by no mortall Sinne it may be diſſolued, but that I may remaine thy faſt freind euen to death, and may neuer againe ſhake hands with the world, fleſh, and deuill, thy ſworne enemies, or any crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture whoſe loue is offenſiue to thee, that I may not only liue but alſo dye louing, and ſo loue thee for euer.</p>
               <p>The third f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eindſhip, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> ô Lord, which out of thy moſt ardent loue thou contracteſt with vs, is by this B. Sacrament of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, by which thou art vnited vnto vs not only in affection, as comonlie freinds are, but alſo in ſubſtance. The firſt freindſhip of Incarnation (if we may iudge of the cauſe by the effect) is the greateſt and nobleſt, becauſe it ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſeth a greater and more noble vnion with God, for that by In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnation man was made the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:26101:62"/>ſonne of God, whereas by the freindſhip of grace and chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, he is only th' adopted ſonne of God, and the frendſhip of Incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation is altogether indiſſoluble, in ſo much that death, which ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated Chriſts ſoule from his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, could not ſeparate his hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine nature from his diuinitie, the freindſhip of grace and chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in this life, is often broken by mortall ſinne. The freindſhip alſo of Incarnation in ſome reſpects exceedeth the freindſhip made by the B. Sacrament, becauſe by In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnation man became God and God man, whereas by the B. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament man is not <hi>Deus, but dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer,</hi> not God, but a bearer of God, in ſoule and ſubſtance, yet in one reſpect the freindſhip made by the Bleſſed Sacrament is greater then that of the Incarnation, becauſe by Incarnation preciſelie taken,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:26101:63"/>that freindſhip was contracted onlie with that particular humain nature which God aſſumed vnto him in the vnitie of perſon; but by the B. Sacrament, Chriſt vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth himſelf in ſubſtance to all thoſe whoe receaue him in it. By Incarnation none but Chriſts hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine nature was formallie dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied and ſanctified, by the B. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament all are ſanctified who worthilie receaue it.</p>
               <p>Yet in this B. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> Sacrament Chriſt hath ſhewed himſelf a greater freind then euer man was to man. me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes freindſhip co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſteth only in affection, but the freindſhip made by the B. Sacrament, importeth a reall vnion of Chriſts ſubſtance with ours, and therefore humain freindſhip cauſeth onlie a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphoricall vnion betwixt tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe who are freinds, but this freind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip implieth a reall vnion of our
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:26101:63"/>ſubſtance with the ſubſtance of Chriſt and of our fleſh and bloud with his. And by humaine freind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip external goods of fortune, as riches, lands, monyes are common betwixt freinds, according to the common ſaieng. <hi>Inter amecos om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia ſunt communia, amongſt freinds al things are common.</hi> But the goods of their bodies as health, ſtrength, beautie &amp;c. are not common, nor can they: but by this freindſhip made in and by this B. Sacrament, Chriſts bodie bloud ſoule yea and diuinitie are imparted to vs, and made common to vs, and our ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance is reallie vnited to his. ô the admirable freindſhip.</p>
               <p>Freinds although they be ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in bodies and places, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> yet by mutuall loue they are vnited in wills, ſoule and ſpirit, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciallie if their freindſhip be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted by grace and charitie, and
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:26101:64"/>therefore of the firſt Chriſtians though ſeparated in bodies &amp; pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce,
<note place="margin">Act 4.</note> S. Luke giueth this teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie: <hi>the multitude of beleeuers had one heart and ſoule.</hi> And Iona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thas his ſoule by freinſhip &amp; loue was ſaid to be <hi>conglutinata</hi> ioyned faſt &amp; as it were glued to the ſoule of Dauid;
<note place="margin">1. Reg. 18.</note>
                  <note place="margin">Lib. 4. Confeſ. c. 6.</note> And S. Auſtin ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of a great freind of his who was dead ſaith. <hi>I thought my ſoule and his ſoule to haue been one ſoule in two bodies, and therefore my life to me was an horrour, becauſe I would not liue halfe, and therefore perchance I feared to die least he shoud dye who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie whom I much loued.</hi> But this vnion betwixt theſe freinds was onlie metaphoricall and in affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, whereas by the freindſhip made in and by the B. Sacrament there is a realle vnion not only of Chriſts ſubſtance with thoſe that receaue him by communion but
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:26101:64"/>alſo of the receauers &amp; commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicants amongeſt themſelues, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they all receauing the ſame indiuiduall bodie of Chriſt, are al reallie vnited in it and by it to one another.</p>
               <p>O admirable freinſhip and no leſſe admirable vnion, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> greater then is the vnion betwixt chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of one Father and mother, their vnion is called conſangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, by which they are vnited in fleſh and bloud which they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſame parents, which is counted a greater tye then any humain freindſhip can make, and yet they receaue not from their parents the ſame indiuiduall fleſh and bloud, either with their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents or with one another, but another, and that diſtinct, though of the ſame Kind; they who receaue this B. Sacrament, do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue the ſame indiuiduall fleſh
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:26101:65"/>and bloud which he hath, and ſo are vnited to him and amongeſt themſelues in one &amp; the ſelfſame fleſh and bloud. By this freind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip we liue not onlie together in one howſe, as other freinds doe, but as Chriſt ſaith Ioan 6.
<note place="margin">Ioan. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>he that eateth his flesh, and drinketh his bloud, abideth in him, and Chriſt in him,</hi> and ſo they liue not onlie together in one howſe, but alſo one with in another.</p>
               <p>O freindſhip excelling all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine freindſhip and euen car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall conſanguinitie and the nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt kinred. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> O how ſhould we lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue this noble freind who out of his exceſſiue loue hath linked vs vnto him, not onlie in affection, as freinds are, nor in the like fleſh and bloud, as children of one Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Mother are, but in the ſelfſame Indiuiduall ſubſtance of which he conſiſteth. O how
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:26101:65"/>ſhould wee loue one another, and euen more then wee doe our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren and ſiſters, becauſe we are linked not onlie in fleſh &amp; bloud of the ſame kind taken from the ſame parents as they are, but in one indiuiduall fleſh, and bloud of Chriſt which we all receaue in this B. Sacrament.</p>
               <p>Freinds at their departure by death or by a long iorney do leaue onlie their freinds an Image or a ringe or ſome other guif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/> and this argueth their great loue: But Chriſt at his departure out of this world (in reſpect of his viſible preſence) hath left vs in this B. Sacrament the beſt thing he had, not an Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge or a ring, or ſuch like, but euen his owne fleſh &amp; bloud, his owne ſelfe, and ſo leauing vs viſible, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth with vs inuiſiblie in this B. Sacrament, and will ſoe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:26101:66"/>with vs to the worlds end. How ſhould we imbrace and loue this our ſo great freind? VVhat ſhal we giue him for this guift? he is more worth ten thouſand times then we are or haue, yet lett vs giue him ourſelues, as he hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen himſelf to vs, and though there be infinite diſparitie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt him and vs, yet he will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of our guift, becauſe it is aſmuch as we can giue.</p>
               <p>Some freinds and Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates who haue made a firme lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue or freindſhip, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="14"/> to make it fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer and more inuiolable, haue let themſelues bloud, and haue ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned it with their bloud. So our B. Sauiour to make a firmer league &amp; freindſhip with vs, did let him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf bloud on the croſſe, and this his bloud he giues vs to drink day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, and his fleſh alſo to eate in the B. Sacrament, thereby to ſigne
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:26101:66"/>this league, and to make it inuio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable. O let vs not on our part break this freindſhip, but let vs ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſigne it with our bloud, if the occaſion be offered, as Chriſt hath ſigned it with his, which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo he giues vs to drinke, that we may neuer forget this league and freindſhip.</p>
               <p>True freinds are readie to dye for one another, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="15"/> as they ſay <hi>Pylades</hi> and <hi>Oreſtes</hi> and others were, thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king themſelues to liue (though dead) ſo long as their freind li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, and to dye (though liuing) when their freind dieth. Our B. Sauiour hath ſacrificed hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelf on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce on the Croſſe by a reall death, and he daylie ſacrificeth himſelf myſticalie in the B. Sacrament for vs, lett vs be then alwaies readie in preparation of minde to dye for him who firſt died for vs, let vs not thinke it much to giue our
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:26101:67"/>life for him who gaue his life for vs, which being the life of God &amp; man, infinitlie ſurpaſſed the liues of all men, though neuer ſo great and manie; yea and of Angels alſo if they could dye, as they may be annihilated.</p>
               <p>O my ſoule do thou reſolue thy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe into loue, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="16"/> to shew thyſelf gratefull to ſo louing a freind, doe thou imitate the Phenix, burne thyſelf in thyne owne flames of loue, that dying in this Fire to the world, this life, and thyſelf, thou maiſt riſe to heauen to an eternall life; ô my ſoule ſtick to this freind ſo faſt, as that neither Father nor Mother, ſiſter nor brother, proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peritie nor aduerſitie, life nor death, nor al the creatures in the world may ſeparate thee from him, but as freinds liue willinglie together, ſo thou maiſt liue in him, and he in thee in this B. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament,
<pb facs="tcp:26101:67" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26101:68" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:26101:68"/>ſo thou maiſt liue with him in the Church militant, that thou maiſt euer liue with him in the Chuch triumphant, ſo thou mayſt liue with him heere by gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce that thou maiſt raigne with him in heauen by glorie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="meditation">
               <head>THE EIGHT MEDITATION <hi>How Christ hath shewed himſelf in this B. Sacrament, a moſt louing ſpouſe.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>O My B. Sauiour, ô louer of ſoules, thou confoundeſt me with thy loue ſhewed to me in this B. Sacrament, by ſo many waies. I haue found thee in it &amp;
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:26101:69"/>by it a bountifull feaſtmaker, &amp; prouident howſe-holder, a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, a Mother, a Freind; &amp; now I finde thee to bee in it and by it a moſt amorous ſpouſe of our ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, that ſo by one Title or other or altogether, thou maiſt wreſt out a reciprocall loue of ours tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards thee. As thou haſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted three freindſhips with vs, as we haue ſeene in the former chapter, ſo haſt thou contracted three Mariages with vs: the firſt by Incarnation, the Second by grace, the third by this B. Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>By Incarnation thou art ſo faſt wedded vnto vs, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> and linked vnto vs by a knott ſo indiſſoluble, that it excelleth the bond of carnall mariaage betwixt man and wife, becauſe carnall mariage is diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by death of both or one of the parties, but the mariage of
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:26101:69"/>Incarnation betwixt God &amp; man is abſolulie indiſſoluble, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that death which ſeparated Chriſt his ſoule from his bodie, could ſeparate neither ſoule nor bodie from the diuinitie, to which they were vnited: and ſo, ſo long as God ſhall be God, he ſhall be man, and man ſhall be God, and the mariage ſhall be eternall, and whereas by mariage all things are common betwixt man and wife, by Incarnation God imparted to our humaine nature all his Goods, and diuine attributes, for that after Incarnation, man became God, and conſequentlie eternall, omnipotent, immenſe &amp;c. by a certain communication which diuines call <hi>communicatio idiomatum,</hi> and man gaue to God all his riches, or rather pouerties, for that after Incarnation God became man and conſequentlie
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:26101:70"/>was borne in tyme of a Virgin-mother, who was borne of a Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin Father before all worlds, and ſo became hungrie and thirſtie, hoat and cold, paſſible and mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall as other men are: and as by carnall mariage man and wife are <hi>vna caro</hi> one fleſh,
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.</note> ſo by this ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage God and man is one flesh, yea one perſon. The Church in which this mariage was made was the ſacred wombe of the Virgin; the Brides God and man: the Prieſt that maried them the Holy Ghoſt, the words by the which the mariage was contracted were. <hi>Ecce Ancilla Domini ſiat mihi ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundum verbum tuum:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luc. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>Behold the handmaid of our Lorde be it done to me according to thy word:</hi> the para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimphe was S. Iohn Baptiſte. But this mariage was made imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatlie onlie betwixt the ſecond perſon in Trinitie God the Sonne
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:26101:70"/>and that humain nature which he tooke of the B. Virgins wombe; yet this mariage is the ground of the two enſuing mariages.</p>
               <p>The ſecond mariage betwixt God and man, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> is contracted by grace &amp; charitie. Of which ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the Prophet Oſee,
<note place="margin">Oſee cap. 2.</note> in the name of God: <hi>I will deſpouſe thee to me for euer, and I will deſpouſe thee to me in Iuſtice &amp;c.</hi> and of this th' Apoſtle alſo ſpeaking ſaith, <hi>I haue deſpouſed you to one man,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>to preſent you a chaſt Virgin vnto Christ.</hi> By this mariage we are ſo deſpouſed and linked to God, that as man and wife are one fleſh, ſo wee and God are one ſpirit, becauſe as S.
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 6.</note> Paul ſaith. <hi>Qui adhaeret Domino vnus ſpiritus eſt, he that cleaneth to our Lord,</hi> (by charitie) <hi>is one ſpirit</hi> with him.</p>
               <p>Man and wife by their bond of mariage are to liue, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> and vſe to liue
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:26101:71"/>in one howſe: but by this maria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge, God dwelleth in vs and we in him, according to thoſe our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiours wordes:
<note place="margin">Io. 14</note> 
                  <hi>If any loue me he will keepe my word, and my Father will loue him, and we will come to him, and will make abode with him:</hi> and that this dwelling and abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding is not onlie with vs, but in vs, it appeareth by other his words:
<note place="margin">Io. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>In that day you shall know that I am in my Father, and you in me, and I in you:</hi> and his diſciple S. Iohn ſaith:
<note place="margin">1. Io. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>God is charitie, and he that abideth in charitie abideth in God and God in him.</hi> So that by this mariage God dwell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th in vs as in his Temple and manſion place, &amp; we in him: yea by this mariage we are as S.
<note place="margin">S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pra 1. Cor. 6.10.17.</note> Paule ſaith <hi>one ſpirit</hi> with God: And Chriſt himſelf prayeth that his Apoſtles and they that beleeued their preaching may <hi>be one</hi> in ſpirit of Charitie, as he
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:26101:71"/>and his Father <hi>are one</hi> in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance.</p>
               <p>VVhereupon the deuout S. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/>
                  <note place="margin">Bern. ſer. 17. in cant.</note> Beanard ſaith. <hi>Quid ergo dicit Fi lius? &amp;c. VVhat doth the Sonne</hi> (of God) <hi>ſay? I am in the Father and the Father in me and we are one. Man ſaith, I ame in God, and God is in me, and we are one ſpirit.</hi> And in the ſame place: <hi>none but a mad man will vſurpe that voice of the onlie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten: I and the Father are one:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bern. ibid.</note> yet <hi>I, though I be but duſte, will not be afraid to ſay this:</hi> I <hi>am one ſpirit with God.</hi> He addeth that man was in God from all eternitie, becauſe God loued man from al eternitie; but God began in time to be in man when man began to loue him. O how ſhould we loue this Spouſe of our ſoules, who is by Charitie ſo wedded vnto vs, as he is not onlie with vs but alſo in vs? becauſe as man and wife
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:26101:72"/>are <hi>vna caro, one flesh,</hi> ſo is he one Spirit with vs. who would for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the loue of ſuch a Spouſe, as God is, who is our Creatour and Sauiour, for the loue of any crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture though neuer ſo deare?</p>
               <p>The thirde mariage betwixt Chriſt and vs, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> is by meanes of the B. Sacrament, by which Chriſt to vs and we to him are vnited, not onlie in mutual loue, but alſo in ſubſtance; becauſe by this B. Sacrament we receaue his body, bloud, ſoule, yea and diuinitie, &amp; our ſubſtance is vnited to his in that his is vnited to ours. And as in carnall mariage all goods are common, euen bodies, becauſe as S.
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 7.</note> Paule ſaith <hi>the woman hath not power of her own body, but her husba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, and the man alſo hath not power of his bodie but the woman.</hi> So by this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament Chriſt communicateth more aboundantlie his grace<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:26101:72"/>then by any other, &amp; his ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, that is his bodie and bloud, ſoule, diuinitie, are ours by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; he as it were taketh poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of our bodie &amp; ſoule when by communion he dwelleth in vs. And as by carnall mariage the man and wife are <hi>vna caro,</hi> one fleſh,
<note place="margin">Hom. 61 Cyrill Alex li. 4. in Ioa. c. 17.</note> ſo doth he in a manner by our receiuing of him mingle his ſubſtance (as S. Chriſoſtome ſaith) with ours, and of two maketh one: and as S. Cyrill ſaith our ſubſtance is made one with his, as waxe vnited to waxe. And ſo as carnal marriage betwixt man and wife is contracted by mutual conſent expreſſed by their words, but is conſummated by vnion of their bodies, ſo a ſpiritual mariage is contracted betwixt vs &amp; Chriſt by charitie, but is not conſumma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted but by vnion of our ſubſtance with his by meanes of this B. Sacr.</p>
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:26101:73"/>
               <p>O my ſoule what an honour is it to bee married to ſuch a ſpouſe; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> more certes the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for a poore maid to be married to a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Emperour, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is a greater diſtance &amp; diſparitie betwixt Chriſt &amp; thee, then betwixt the pooreſt begget and the richeſt Emperour. ô how didſt thou loue me ſweete Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour! who vouchſafeſt to take me thy poore creature for thy ſpouſe. And if I conſider what thou ſuffredſt to pourchaſe me for thy Spouſe, thy loue will more ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare: If an Emperour ſhould ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard his life to winne the loue of a poore maide, how amorous ſhould he be thought to be of her. Thou ô Lord ſheddeſt thy bloud to winne my loue and boughtſt me with it to be thy ſpouſe, ſo that as Sephora ſayde to Moyſes that he was <hi>a bloudie ſpouſe vnto her,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 4</note> becauſe ſhe was enforced to
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:26101:73"/>circumciſe her ſonne to ſaue Moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes his life, ſo much more ô my ſoule maiſt thou ſaie to thy ſpou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe Chriſt Ieſus. Thou a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t a blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die ſpouſe vnto me, who ſheddedſt thy bloud and ſufferdſt thy bitter paſſion to marrie me by thy grace and by this B. Sacrament, giue me grace to be alwaies readie in mi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de to ſhed my bloud for thee, if occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion ſhall preſent it ſelf, that I may alſo be a bloudie ſpouſe to thee. To this I ame inuited by thy bloud which I ſo often drinke in the B. Sacrament.</p>
               <p>It is commaunded in Geneſis that man ſhould leaue Father and Mother toad here to his wife, and,
<note place="margin">Gen. 2.</note> the ſame commandement is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to the wife in regarde of her huſband: much more ſhouldſt thou (my ſoule) rather leaue car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall parents and wordlie riches &amp; pleaſures; then to leaue by ſinne
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:26101:74"/>this thy ſo louinge ſpouſe;
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.</note> Thou commandeſt allſo ô deare Spouſe that men ſhould loue their wiues, do thou obſerue this lawe which thou haſt made, and do thou loue me thy Spouſe, betro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed to thee by charitie and this B. Sacrament, and giue me grace alwaies to loue thee, neuer to offend thee. O how happie art thou my ſoule, who art eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pouſed to ſo noble and ſo chaſt a Spouſe as Chriſt,
<note place="margin">In offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio S. Agnetis.</note> 
                  <hi>whoſe Father knew no woman, whoſe Mother knew no man,</hi> who is a Spouſe more beautifull then the Sunne, more rich then heauen and earth, more noble then all the Emperours that euer were: <hi>VVhom if thou loueſt thou art chast,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ibid.</note> 
                  <hi>if thou tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chest thou art cleane, and vndefiled, if thou marrieſt thou remaineſt a Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin.</hi> O my ſweete Sauiour loue me, I ame thy Spouſe, ô my ſoule
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:26101:74"/>loue thy Sauiour, he is thy Spouſe: And as man and wife do ſo loue that they are neuer well but when they are together; ſo ô ſweet Ieſus my deare Spouſe let me neuer thinke my ſelfe well but when I ame with thee, and thou with me, by frequent com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion and receauing of this B. Sacrament, that liuing with thee in this B. Sacrament, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequentlie in the Church mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant, where only it is lawfullie miniſtred and receiued, I may liue and dwell with thee for euer in the Church Triumphant.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="meditation">
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:26101:75"/>
               <head>THE NINTH MEDITATION <hi>VVhat a Phyſicia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt hathe shewed himſelfe in this B. Sacrament.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>GOD Almightie created man in good health, ſound and whole both in body and ſoule, beſtowinge on him the tree of life which would haue preſerued his bodie from diſtemperatures, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes and death, and endewing him with originall Iuſtice, which ſo ſubiected his bodie to his ſoule, and ſenſualitie to reaſon, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour part of his ſoule to the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour, and that to God, that in
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:26101:75"/>his ſoule there was no inordinate paſſion, no ſinne, nor ſpirituall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmitie, But he not knowinge how to vſe this his felicitie, by a willfull ſurfette taken by eating the forbidden fruit, diſtempered his bodie with mortalitie, from whence all diſeaſes of the bodie and death it ſelf proceed, and by his diſobedience caſt his ſoule at one time into as many diſeaſes as inordinate paſſions, which diuers haue reduced to fowre, which they call, <hi>vulnera animae, woundes of the ſoule,</hi> reſiding in fowre princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall powers and faculties of the ſoule. The vnderſtanding, whoſe obiect is truth, and whoſe perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is knowledge, was obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and darkned by ignorance. The will, whoſe marke, at which ſhe aimeth, is good, &amp; whoſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection is loue, was infected with malice, The iraſcible part, whoſe
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:26101:76"/>obiect is difficultie, and whoſe glorie is victorie ouer difficultie, was weakned with infirmitie. The concupiſcible part, whoſe obiect was moderat delight, and whoſe felicitie was contentment, was galled with the itching and ill pleaſing ſore of concupiſcence.</p>
               <p>And thus this Samaritan deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cending from Heruſalem that is Paradiſe, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> from which now he was baniſhed, vnto Hierico this mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal and miſerable world, the vale of miſerie, fell into the hands of theeues, the deuills, who diſpoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led him of his armour of originall Iuſtice and wounded him in bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and ſoule,
<note place="margin">Luc. 10.</note> yet <hi>ſemiuiu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> relicto.</hi> Leauing him halfe aliue becauſe though he was diſpoiled of all ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernaturall graces, yet he loſt no naturall perfection, though he was alſo weakened in that. By this miſerable and woefull wight
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:26101:76"/>thus miſerablie ſpoiled &amp; woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the <hi>Preiſte</hi> &amp; <hi>Leuite</hi> paſſed,
<note place="margin">Luc. 10.</note> but could not cure him, or helpe him, becauſe the old law could onlie tell the diſeaſe, but could not cure it by grace, becauſe though their law was giuen by Moyſes, yet grace by Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Thou therefore ô ſweete ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> ô moſt expert and merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full phyſitian, who cameſt to ſaue ſinners, and to heale the woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and diſeaſed, by the oyle of thy merc e, &amp; wine of thy bloud, which thou ſhedſt in thy paſſion &amp; appliedſt, &amp; as it were powredſt forth in the B. Sacrament, haſt on thy parte cured this miſerable wight, man, and all mankind. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 
               </p>
               <p>Thy Sacraments ô Lord, which thou inſtitutedſt, are ſo many ſalues, and remedies againſt the ſores, wounds, and diſeaſes
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:26101:77"/>of our ſoule. Baptiſme cureth the wound of originall ſinne: the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of Pennance is a reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die againſt the ſinnes that are committed after Baptiſme: Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimonie is a ſalue ordained a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the wound of concupiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, which galleth the concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcible part: Confirmation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt infirmitie in the Iraſcible part: The B. Sacrament after we are cured, nouriſheth vs in a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall life: Extreme vnction taketh away the reliques of ſinne: Order maketh vnder Phyſitians, who vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Chriſt, and by vertue and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie from him do miniſter the aforeſayd Sacraments and <hi>remitte ſinnes.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Io. 20.</note> ô Soueraigne and ſauing Phyſitian.</p>
               <p>By thy holy word alſo, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred ſcripture thou haſt ſhewed thy ſelf to be our Phyſitian, for that euerie word of this ſacred
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:26101:77"/>ſcripture is a ſimple, euerie ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce a ſalue againſt ſinne, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by reading holy ſcripture or hearing of it read and rightlie interpreted, many thousa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des haue been conuerted, many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands haue been ſaued: O ſweet Ieſus in whoſe name dwelleth ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation: O heauenlie Phyſitian who haſt prouided ſo many reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies againſt ſinne, ſo many helpes to ſaluation.</p>
               <p>Nay all Chriſte his life was a ſhoppe full of drugges, ſalues, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> &amp; remedies againſt ſinne. Euerie praier he made, euerie exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: euery parable he ſpake, euerie miracle he wrought, euerie word he vttered, euerie good worke he did, euerie ſtepp he walked, euerie teare that fell from his eies, euerie droppe of bloud he ſhed for vs, euerie laſh at the pillar, euerie pricke of the
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:26101:78"/>thornes, euerie pearcing of the nailes in his hands and feete, the hunger and thirſt he endured, euerie paine &amp; pange he ſuſtained on the croſſe, were a ſalue and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie againſt ſinne. So that if now the prophet Hieremie ſhould aſke of vs Chriſtians, as he did heretofore of the Iewes,
<note place="margin">Hier. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>is there no roſen in Galaad,</hi> in the Church of God? is there no Phyſitian there? we might anſwer, yes Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remie in the Church of Chriſt there is <hi>roſen</hi> and all manner of ſalues and remedies, againſt all our ſpirituall wounds &amp; diſeaſes. And in this Church there is a head Phyſitian Chriſt Ieſus, and thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of vnder-Phyſitians, euen as many as there are lawfull Prieſts, who can abſolue from ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and miniſter Sacraments, and preach the word of God, and thereby remitte all ſinnes
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:26101:78"/>and cure all our ſpirituall diſeaſes.</p>
               <p>Phyſitians do companie more with the ſicke then the whole, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> they are much in hoſpitalls by ſicke &amp; infirme perſons, with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they deuiſe about their ſicknes, them they ſeeke to comfort. And thou ô heauenlie Phyſitian, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing thy Fathers Pallace deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dedſt into the Hoſpitall of this world, where are as many Lazars, ſicke and infirme perſons, as there are ſinners, and with them whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt thou liuedſt on earth was thy conuerſation, ſometimes with ſcribes and Phariſies, ſometimes with Publicans, ſometimes with harlots; and all thy talke and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes, parables, and preachings &amp; miracles were practiſed amon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt them, and for them; yea thou ſateſt at table with <hi>Publicanes and ſinners</hi> &amp; by that familiaritie gai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedſt them,
<note place="margin">Math. 9. Mat. 2.</note> and by thy wholſome
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:26101:79"/>exhortatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s curedſt them of their ſinnes. And when the Scribes &amp; Phariſies found fault with this,
<note place="margin">Luc. 5.</note> thou anſwerdſt them. <hi>The whole haue no need of a Phyſitian, but they that are ill at eaſe, for I came not to call the luſt but Sinners.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But eſpeciallie ô my good God thou haſt ſhewed thy ſelf a moſt lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing and mercifull Phyſitian in this B. Sacrament, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> where thou gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt vs in a moſt admirable man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner thy ſacred bodie and bloud, which are moſt ſoueraigne me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decines, againſt all ſpirituall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes, for as whileſt thou liuedſt a mortall life with vs in this world, <hi>vertue went forth from thee and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led all</hi> of their corporall diſeaſes,
<note place="margin">Luc. 6.</note> ſo in this B. Sacrament, where thou art reallie, vertue iſſueth from thy ſacred body and bloud, and healeth and cureth all ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall diſeaſes, and whereas cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:26101:79"/>medecines and potions do reſtore vs only to health of bodie, and ſo conſerue life for a time. This medecine of thy fleſh and bloud giueth life euerlaſting both to ſoule and bodie, and therefore thou thy ſelfe ſaiſt, <hi>he that eateth my flesh and drinketh my bloud,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Io. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>hath life euerlaſting and I will raiſe him vp in the laſt daye;</hi> and he giueth the reaſon hereof, <hi>for my flesh</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is meat indeed and my bloud is drinke indeed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Other Phyſicians to cure diuerſe diſeaſes muſt preſcribe diuers medecines and potions, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of diuers ingrediences: but thou with one potion of thy ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred bloud, which we drinck in this B. Sacrament, cureſt all diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. Other Phyſitians will mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter to their patients bitter po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, but themſelues will not drinck of them, but thou at thy
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:26101:80"/>laſt ſupper dranckſt a health to vs of thy bloud, which was bitter to thee in thy paſſion, when it was ſhed, but pleaſant to vs, and ſo pleaſant that it taketh away the bitternes from all the ſuffrances and aduerſities which we endure, as it appeareth in the Apoſtles and our martyrs who <hi>with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered</hi> for thee.
<note place="margin">Act. 5.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Other Phyſicians to cure their patiens of their ague will let them bloud, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> yea and ſometimes launce them and ſcarifie them, but will not looſe a drop of their owne bloud for them: but thou ô lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing Phyſician! dideſt let thyſelfe blood euen at the heart to cure our ague of ſinne. And this thy bloud thou giueſt vnto vs in this Bleſſed Sacrament.</p>
               <p>Other Phyſicians will preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribe to their patients abſtinence and faſting, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> for to diminiſh the
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:26101:80"/>heate of their ague, by dimini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing the humours which nouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed it, but will not faſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, but thou faſtedſt fortie daies and for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ie nights for vs. Other Phyſitians will endeuour to take the ague and diſeaſe from the ſicke perſon,
<note place="margin">Math. 4.</note> but will not take it to themſelues to ridd him of it, but thou haſt taken our ſpirituall ague of ſinne on thy ſelfe to free vs f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it, according as thy Apoſtle S. Peeter teſtifieth, ſayeng,
<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>who himſelf bare our ſinnes in his bodie vpon the tree.</hi> Not that thou tookſt the mallice of ſinne (of which thy ſacred humanitie was vnca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable) but that thou enduredſt in thy bodie, and on the Croſſe the paine due to ſinne, in ſatisf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing for it by thy death and bitter paſſion, and by ſuffering the paine, thou haſt cured the ague, and this thy paſſion is repreſented and applied
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:26101:81"/>by this Holy Sacrament.</p>
               <p>O moſt charitable Phyſitian: ô my ſoule what thankes ſhouldſt thou giue to this thy Phyſitian for this B. Sacrament, ſo ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne againſt all our ſpirituall diſeaſes? O with what diſpoſition ſhouldeſt thou come to receaue this ſo wholeſome Phyſicke, which cureth all veniall ſinnes, yea &amp; mortall alſo, if thou haue no knowledge nor conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>?</p>
               <p>O my ſoule when by this B. Sacrament thou art cured of thy ſpiritual diſeaſes, remember thoſe words ſpoken by this thy Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian to the lame man at the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batica Piſcina.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioan 5.</note> 
                  <hi>I am ſanus es noli am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plius peccare, now thou art made whole ſinne no more:</hi> now that thou art cured by ſuch ſoueraigne Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke, do thou take heede of reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diuation and falling into ſicknes again, for that this thy ingratitude
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:26101:81"/>will be greater, and thy ſinne and ſicknes more hardlie cured: But do thou frequent often this B. Sacrament, by deuout com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion and receauing, and then by it thou wilt be more and more nouriſhed in grace, &amp; fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied againſt ſinne; then by vertue of this Spirituall food thou ſhalt one day come to ſitte at table with the Angels and Saints; and then thou ſhalt feede not of Chriſt his bodie and bloud, as now thou doeſt in this B. Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but of the diuinitie of God, by cleare viſion and fruition of him; then thou ſhalt taſt how ſweet God is in his Godhead, then thou ſhalt euer feede of the diuinitie, yet neuer loath it, then thou ſhalt alwaies drinke of that fountane of pleaſure, and yet be euer more and more deſirous to drinke: Then all bliſſe, happines
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:26101:82"/>and pleaſure ſhall euer fill thee, and yet thou ſhall neuer be ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied,
<note place="margin">Aug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trac 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n Euang. Io. in fine.</note> yea (to vſe S. Auſtines words) <hi>thou shalt euer be ſatisfied, &amp; yet neuer ſatisfied, for if I ſaye thou shalt not be ſatisfied, hunger shall be there; if I ſay that thou shalt be ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied I feare loathing There shall nether be hunger nor loathing I know not what to ſaye.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="meditation">
               <head>THE TENTH MEDITATION <hi>How good a Shepheard and Paſtour Chriſt hath shewed himſelfe in this B. Sacrament.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ALthough (ô my ſweet Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour) thou art not onlie man but alſo God, yet thou ſtileſt not
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:26101:82"/>thyſelf ſo willinglie by names ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from thy Godhead, as <hi>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour</hi> of heauen and Earth <hi>Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent, Immenſe, King of Kings,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Reg.</note> 
                  <hi>Lord of Lords, God and Lord of hostes,</hi> (which are names of Maieſtie &amp; terrour, and by which thou waſt moſt often called in the old law) as by names taken from thy hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main nature, to wit, <hi>Ieſus</hi> and <hi>Sauiour, Redeemer, light of the world, bread of life, and the like,</hi> which are names ſounding and impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting loue, mercie and benignitie; but aboue all the name of Paſtour pleaſeth thee, that implying grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt loue and charitie; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thou profeſſeſt thyſelf to be a <hi>Good Paſtour,</hi> and ſuch an one, as is readie <hi>to giue his life for his sheepe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Io. 10.</note> then which there can be no grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter charitie.</p>
               <p>Other ſhepheardes in ſome Countries, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> to winne the loue of
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:26101:83"/>their ſheepe, and to familiarize themſelues the better with them, do inueſt themſelues with ſheep-skinnes, with the wooll out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards; and thou (ô louing Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtour) that thou mights be the leſſe terrible, and more amiable to vs thy ſheepe, wouldſt not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in thy glorious habit and weed of thy diuinitie,
<note place="margin">Exod. 19. &amp; 20.</note> nor in fire, nor lightning, nor thunder, nor in darke and terrible clouds, as thou didſt in the old law, which was a law of terrour; but wouldſt put on the habit and fleeſe of our humain nature, and ſo appeare &amp; bee man with men: that ſo men might conuerſe with thee with leſſe feare, more loue, and fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaritie:
<note place="margin">Phil. 2.</note> for thou <hi>exinanitedst thy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, taking the forme of a Seruant, made into the ſimilitude of men, and in shape found as man:</hi> that being man thou mightſt the better con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:26101:83"/>with thy ſheepe, who are men. In this ſhape of man, thou waſt ſo gratefull to the Iewes, that whereas before that thou putſt on this alluring habit, they durſt not approach to the mountaine, where thou exhibitedſt thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, nor could endure to heare thy voice,
<note place="margin">Ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 20.</note> but cried to haue Moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, not thee to ſpeake vnto them; ſince that thou appearedſt in the forme of man,
<note place="margin">Tit. 3.</note> and that the <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nignitie and kindnes towards man of our Sauiour God, appeared,</hi> Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of the Iewes, followed thee to heare thy preaching, and to ſee thy miracles, and good examples: and ſince that like a good ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard in this forme of man (for in the forme of God thou couldſt not) thou diedſt for mankind, all nations haue flocked vnto thee, and will do till the worlds end. O happie wee, who are go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerned
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:26101:84"/>by a Paſtour of our owne Kind, in our owne ſhape, and him ſo benigne, milde, and chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table.</p>
               <p>Paſtours and ſhepheards do gouerne their ſheepe by their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorall ſtaffe or hooke, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> by their owne call or whiſtle, or by their dogge; &amp; theſe ſhepheards bring them to paſtures, or feelds moſt fit for them to graſe in, and where is moſt fit nourriture for them: ſo thou a louing Paſtour, gouerneſt vs by the ſtaffe of thy Paſtorall authoritie, which thou haſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted to thy vnder Paſtours, and doctours of the Church, yet ſo, as whileſt they direct vs out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardlie by lawes and comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dementes, thou directeſt vs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardlie by grace, which giueth vs force to obey them; whileſt they gouerne and feede vs out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardlie, by preaching &amp; expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:26101:84"/>ſcripture, thou preacheſt inwardlie by thy grace &amp; inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; whileſt they miniſter the externall ſignes of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, thou feedeſt vs inwardlie by the grace, which thou giueſt, as the principall Agent; and they giue, as miniſters, the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as inſtruments inſtituted by thee for our ſanctification; and in theſe paſtures, by this fodder moſt fatting and nouriſhing, thou feedeſt thy ſheepe. And if whileſt thy ſheepe are grazing and fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in the medowes of holy Scripture (of which euerie ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence is as graſſe to feed them) if whileſt they are feeding on the ſodder of the holy Sacraments, the Infernall wolfe, the deuill, or the worlde and fleſh ſeeke to moleſt them by their tentations; if the Heretike by his falſe call, and whiſtle, ſeeke to deceaue
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:26101:85"/>them, then the vnder Paſtours doe lay about them with their Paſtorall ſtaffe, yea and as Chriſt his doggs they barke at them, and chaſe them away, being not, as the Iewiſh paſtours were,
<note place="margin">Eſai. 36.</note> 
                  <hi>dumme doggs not able to barke.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the old law (ô louing Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtour) thou fedſt thy ſheepe with figuratiue Sacraments, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> which were no cauſes, but bare ſignes of grace, and ſo could giue no grace, &amp; therefore by thy Apoſtle are called <hi>egena elementa,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal 4.</note> 
                  <hi>poore ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments;</hi> but in the new law thou feedeſt vs with Sacraments, which are not onlie ſignes, but alſo cauſes of grace; and which do ſanctifie, nouriſh, and feed our ſoules; and therefore thy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet Ezechiel forſeeing theſe our happie times, in which thou fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt vs ſo aboundantlie,
<note place="margin">Ezech. 34.</note> ſayth in thy name: <hi>In the moſt plentifull Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stures
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:26101:85"/>will I feed them, and in the high mountaines of Iſrael shall be their paſtures: there shall they rest on the greene graſſe, and in fatte paſtures they shall be fedde vpon the mountains of Iſrael:</hi> O the loue thou haſt ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wed to thy Chriſtian ſheepe, in prouiding them ſo fatte paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures!</p>
               <p>And in this thy loue hath ſhewed it ſelf the greater, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> becauſe thou ſhewedst it vnto them, after that they had forſaken thee by ſinne, and were quite lost; for thou leftst the 99. ſheepe to witt the 9. orders of Angels in the deſert,
<note place="margin">Mat. 12.</note> that is in heauen, which before thy comming into this world by Incarnation, was a deſert place, and inacceſſible to men, becauſe thou waſt not Incarnat for An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, much leſſe didst thou ſuffer for them, but leauing them, thou camest to vs by Incarnation in
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:26101:86"/>our forme and ſhape; and thou camest to ſeeke mankind thy lost ſheepe, &amp; hauing found him, thou carriedſt him vpon thy ſhoulders, when thou ſufferedſt on the croſſe for him, and broughtſt this ſtrayd ſheepe to the folde of the Church, where he is fedde in plentifull and fatte paſtures:
<note place="margin">Tertul. lib. de pudi. cap. 7.</note> And therefore in the primitiue Church (as Tertullian witneſſeth) thou waſt pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traited vpon the holy chalices, like a ſhepheard carying his loſt ſheepe on his ſhoulders.</p>
               <p>Iacob the Patriarch a ſhepheard and figure of thee our good Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtour, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 31.</note> ſaid to <hi>Laban,</hi> that he had kept his ſheepe twentie yeares, and that none of his ſheepe or goates periſhed, but <hi>he reſtored the damage. Daie and night</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>was I parched with heate, and with freſt, and sleepe did flie from myne
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:26101:86"/>eyes.</hi> But thou, (ô my Sauiour, ô my carefull Paſtour) playedſt the Paſtour amongeſt vs aboue thirtie yeares (for euen by the merites of thy Infancie thou feddſt vs dare and n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ght) thou trauelledſt for vs, by night by praier, by daie by preaching, teaching, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of miracles; thou ſuffredſt heate and colde, hunger &amp; thirſt; thou faſtedſt fortie daies, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie nights to feed vs; thou waſt circumciſed, thou waſt whipped at a pillar, crowned with thornes, nailed on a Croſſe, where like a good ſhepheard thou diedſt for vs, leaſt the Infernal wolfe ſhould deuoure vs. O how great muſt thy loue to thy ſheepe be, which made thee ſuffer ſo much for them? Iacobs loue was ſo great to Rachel that he ſerued Laban twice ſeauen yeares for her;
<note place="margin">Gen. 29.</note> but thy loue was ſo great that it cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:26101:87"/>thee to ſuffer a moſt painfull life of more then, 3 yeares for thy ſheepe; and this thy painfull life thou alſo concludedſt with a moſt painfull and ſhamefull death for them. O my ſoule neuer do thou ſo much as thinke of leauing ſo louing a Paſtour; neuer do thou ſtraic from his fold, nor from his ſo plentifull paſtures, as ſinners, and eſpeciallie Heretikes do.</p>
               <p>But eſpeciallie, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> ô my ſweet Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thou haſt ſhewed thyſelf <hi>a good Pastour,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Io. 10.</note> in this B. Sacrament: A good Paſtour will die for his ſheepe, ſo didſt thou dye reallie on the Croſſe for vs; and myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>callie in this B. Sacrament; where thy death and paſſion is repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and applied to thy ſheepe, &amp; whereas other ſhepheards do onelie feede their ſheepe with haye, graſſe and ſuch like fodder, thou, o moſt louing Pastour, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:26101:87"/>vs thy owne fleſh to eate and thy owne bloud to drinke, which by their vnion with the diuinitie are the most nouriſhing food that can be, next vnto the diuinitie it ſelf, on which thy glorious ſheepe, the Saints &amp; Angels in Heauen, doe feede by cleare viſion and fruition of it. O wonderfull loue of a Pastour! ô loue and charitie aboue all other loues &amp; charities. O loue aboue all loues not onlie of Pastours, but euen of Fathers and Mothers. <hi>Quis Paſtor</hi> (ſaith S.
<note place="margin">Chryſ. hom. 60. ad pop. Antioc.</note> Chriſostome) <hi>oues paſcit proprio cruore? &amp; quid dico Paſtor? Matres multae ſunt quae post partus dolores ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lios alijs tradunt nutricibus; hoc au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem ipſe non eſt paſsus, ſed ipſe nos pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prio ſanguine paſcit, &amp; per omnia nos ſibi coagmentat; what Paſtour doth feede his sheepe with his owne bloud? And what do I ſay, pastour? many mothers there are who giue their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:26101:88"/>to other nurces; but he would not ſuffer this, but he himſelf doth feed vs with his owne bloud, and altogether doth ioyne vs vnto him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O my ſoule how canst thou be cruell like a wolfe, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> who feedest on this milde lambe? how canst thou be otherwiſe then chast, who feedest of the Virgin Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Sonne, and of his chast fleſh and bloud? how canst thou be prophane, who art nouriſhed with ſo holie and ſacred meate &amp; drinke? how canst thou be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, who art fedde with ſo ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall foode, as is the fleſh &amp; bloud of Christ, ſpiritualized by the diuinitie it ſelfe? how diuine ſhouldst thou bee, who art a God on earth (by participation) who art feasted with ſuch diuine meate and drinke?</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> Graunt me (ô ſweet Ieſus) that as thou hast ſhewed thyſelf a
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:26101:88"/>good Paſtour, to me, &amp; to vs all, ſo I may ſhewe my ſelfe a good &amp; gratefull ſheepe. The ſheepe is obedient to the ſhepheards whiſtle, &amp; followeth none other; make me obedient to thy voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and diuine inſpirations; and let me not harken to the falſe whiſtle of falſe Prophets, nor to the inchanting voices of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, world, and fleſh. A ſheepe is a moſt fearfull creature, who when he runneth with the reſt of the flocke, is afraid of the noiſe of his owne &amp; his fellowes feete; and if he eſpie the wolfe, though a farre of, he fleeth from him ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain lie &amp; repaireth to his flocke, folde, and ſhepheard. Giue me grace to feare, as Iob did, all my owne actions, and as ſoone as ether world, fleſh, or deuill do beginne to tempte me, to flie from them, &amp; to auoid preſentlie
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:26101:89"/>all occaſions of ſinne, and to haue preſent recourſe to thee, my care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſhepheard, and to thy Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and other meanes thou haſt prouided vs againſt ſinne.</p>
               <p>Sheepe are ſimple, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> my<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>de, and free from galle; and euen when they are carried to be butchered, they kicke not, as the horſe doth; they cry not, as the hogge doth; they durre not with their hornes, as the bull and cowe doth; they bite not, as the wolfe and dogge doth; but they ſuffer patientlie without cryinge, without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting: Onelie, whethere they be grazing or chewing the cudde, whethere they haue graſſe in their mouth, or the Butchers knife at their throate, before the ſhearer, and the butcher they are mute; or they vſe onelie their innocent <hi>Ba;</hi> that onelie is their crye in proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie and aduerſitie; graunt me, ô
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:26101:89"/>my deare Paſtour, and ſweet ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, to imitate this m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>de pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience and in aduerſitie and proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peritie, in ſicknes and health, in riches and pouertie, to be euer the ſame and to vſe the ſame ſheepiſh <hi>Ba,</hi> which Iob vſed:
<note place="margin">Iob. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>Our Lord gaue, and our Lord hath taken awaye, as it hath pleaſed our Lord, ſo is it done, the name of our Lord be bleſsed,</hi> aſwell for the one, as for the other; aſwel for takeing away, as giuing; aſwell for ſicknes, as health; aſwell for pouertie, as ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; aſwell for aduerſitie, as proſperitie; yea more for this, then that; becauſe aduerſitie borne patientlie is a greater benefite then whatſoeuer proſperitie. O ſweete Ieſus! make me ſimple and meeke, as a ſheepe, as thou thyſelf waſt, who therefore bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt vs to learne of thee;
<note place="margin">Mat. 11. 2. Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>for that thou art meeke and humble of heart:</hi>
                  <pb n="132" facs="tcp:26101:90"/>make me innocent as a lamb, yea as an infant newlie borne.</p>
               <p>The ſhepheard knoweth his ſheepe, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/>
                  <note place="margin">Io. 10.</note> &amp; they him, &amp; as he hath his eye alwayes on them, ſo they haue alwaies their eyes open to him. O louing Paſtour and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, let thy carefull eye be euer on me, and then I can not periſh; and let my eye be alwaies on thee, let me alwaies thinke on thee, and thy commandements, and the benefits thou haſt beſtowed on mee. It is a great honour to be knowne of thee, to haue but thy good looke, and gracious regard; and it is as great a miſerie not to be knowne thus of thee, and to heare that dolefull voice,
<note place="margin">Mat 25.</note> 
                  <hi>neſcio vos, I know you not.</hi> O let me neuer heare that voice. And for me to know thee alwaies, to haue myne eyes ſo ſetled on thee, as to haue thee alwaies in my ſight, is a great
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:26101:90"/>comfort, a great ſecuritie, a great bridle, and reſtraint from ſinne; and as great a ſpurre to all vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue: for who can do ill, who can do otherwiſe then well, who hath thee alwaies in his ſight? who knoweth that thy eyes are vpon him, that he is neuer out of thy kenning.</p>
               <p>O ſweet Ieſus, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> o louing Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtour, my ſoule is a ſheepe of thy flock and fold, &amp; it hath wandred and ſtraied from thee, and thy flocke by ſinne; but thou haſt by thy grace ſought it, and found it, &amp; brought it backe on thy ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders: giue me conſtancie that I neuer ſtraie from thee againe. O deare Paſtour, my ſoule is a ſheepe of thy flocke and fold; I commend it to thy care; it is thy ſheepe bought and redeemed with thy precious bloud; it is thy ſheepe fedde in this B. Sacrament
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:26101:91"/>with thy fleſh and bloud; it is thy ſheepe, gouerne it, rule it, direct it, protect it, guide it in the pathes of Saluation, that it may one day graze and feede with thy Angels and Sainctes in the mountaine of Heauen, and on thy ſacred diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, which onelie can make it happie: Graunt this ô my louing Paſtour, o graunt it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theſe former</hi> 10. <hi>Meditations may be read more, or fewer according to the deuotion of him who intendeth to receaue this B. Sacrament; and either immediatlie, or ſome daye or dayes before communion; But theſe which follow are to be read either immediatlie before, or imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatlie after communion.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="meditation">
               <pb n="135" facs="tcp:26101:91"/>
               <head>THE 11. MEDITATION <hi>VVith what feare and reuerence, and acknowledgment of vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thines, the deuout receauer is to come to this Bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>NOw therefore, ô my ſoule! ſeeing thou perceiueſt what a Good man of the houſe, what an Hoſte, what a Father, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, friend, ſpouſe, Phyſitian, and Paſtour thy B. Sauiour hath ſhewed himſelf to thee in this B. Sacrament, &amp; what he beſtoweth on thee by it, and in it, to witt, his owne fleſh and bloud, himſelf,
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:26101:92"/>God and man, infinite in all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, and the fountaine of all grace; endeuour as much as thou canſt, by his grace, to diſpoſe thyſelf to come vnto him, and to receaue him in this Holie Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as worthilie, as humain frailtie and pouertie will permit.</p>
               <p>And firſt thou muſt come to him with a great filiall feare, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> and reuerence, his Maieſtie (though vailed with the formes of bread and wine) requiring it. Dauid in ſpirit forſeeing this great and wonderous myſterie of the B. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament ſaith: <hi>memoriam fecit mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabilium ſuorum,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſa. 110.</note> 
                  <hi>miſericors &amp; miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rator dominus, eſcam dedit timentibus ſe: He hath made a memorie of his marueilous works, a mercifull and pitifull Lord: he hath giuen meat to them, that feare him.</hi> This memorie of his marueilous works is this feaſt of the B. Sacrament, where
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:26101:92"/>is nothing but marueills &amp; won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, which alſo conſiſt not in folding vp of napkins in many faſhions, but in the cookerie and art ſhewed in this feaſt; in which, bread by the force of Chriſts owne words, is conuerted into his bodie, wine into his bloud; in which the accidents and exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall forines of bread and wine ſtand alone without bread and wine, which were their ſubiects; in which Chriſts bodie extended in it ſelfe, is wholie contained in a litle hoſte, and in euerie parte of it, in which one body is on diuers Altars, and in diuerſe places; in which Chriſts bodie is dailie eaten his bloud dailie drunke, yet ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer conſumed; in which the ſame Chriſt is <hi>conuiua &amp; conuinium,</hi> the feaſt maker, gueſt, and feaſt, in which the ſame Chriſt is the Prieſt, the ſacrifice, and the God
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:26101:93"/>to whom this ſacrifice is offered: and therefore Dauid explicating what the memorie of theſe mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueils is, ſaith: <hi>Eſcam dedit timenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>busſe:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſa. 110.</note> 
                  <hi>he hath giuen meate to them that feare him,</hi> as if he had ſaid, he hath made a memorie of marueil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les in the meate which he hath giuen; and this meat he giueth to them, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
                  <hi>that feare him:</hi> who only can frutefullie receaue it.</p>
               <p>O my ſoule thou beleeueſt, that Chriſt God and man, is as trulie in this B. Sacrament, which thou intendeſt to receaue, as he was in his Virgin Mothers wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be, as he was here on earth, and as he is now in Heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, though in an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther manner; and thou beleeueſt that there is no more betwixt him and thee, when thou approacheſt tereceaue him, then the thinne courtaines of the accidents and formes of bread and wine drawne betwixt him and thy ſight. And
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:26101:93"/>if thou wouldſt ſtand with great reuerence in the preſence of a mortall Emperour or King, though a man as thou art; and though there were a thinne cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine drawne betwixt him and thee, eſpeciallie if the courtaine were ſo thinne, as he might ſee thee through it: with what reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ſhouldſt thou ſtand or kneele in the preſence of Chriſt Ieſus, God and man, and King and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour of heauen and earth; there being no more betwixt him and thee, then the courtaines of the formes of bread and wine, which are thinner then the thinneſt taffeta or cypres, becauſe in thoſe, though neuer ſo thinne, there is matter and ſubſtance, whereas in the accidents of bread &amp; wine there is no ſubſtance at all of bread and wine; and through the which Chriſt, God &amp; Man, ſeeth thee and all thy actions both interiour
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:26101:94"/>and exteriour? VVith what reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence (I ſay) ſhouldſt thou come to this B. Sacrament, in which thou beleeueſt to be the King of glorie, though with corporall ſight thou canſt not ſee him?</p>
               <p>O conſider (my ſoule) that when thou receiueſt this dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſacrifice and Sacrament, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> thou haſt on thy tongue more then tongue can explicate, in thy mouth more then heauen &amp; earth containe, in thy heart more then heart can conceaue. Thou recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt him, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Angels adore, and tremble to behold his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie. In the old law the Iewes were commaunded not ſo much as to touch the mountaine, on which the law of God was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen;
<note place="margin">Exod. 29.</note> and ſhalt thou thinke thy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe worthie to touch the Altar, where the law giuer is reſident, yea to touch himſelf, &amp; to receaue
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:26101:94"/>him into thy mouth and ſtomake? If the <hi>Bethſamites</hi> to the number of <hi>ſeauentie men of the people,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Reg. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>and fiftie thouſand of the common people,</hi> for curious he gazing at the Ark, which was but a figure of this B Sacrament;
<note place="margin">2 Reg. 6.</note> if <hi>Oza</hi> for touching it irreuerentlie, were ſtricken with ſodaine death; ſhalt thou, ô my ſoule! if irreuerentlie or vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thilie thou receaue this B. Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the Ark of the new law, thinke to goe ſcotfree? Noe, Noe. S. Paule aſſureth thee,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>that he that eateth and drinketh vnworthilie</hi> (the bodie and bloud of Chriſt) <hi>eateth and drinketh iudgment to himſelf, not diſcerning the bodie of our Lord.</hi> Yea, ſaith he, becauſe you eate and drinke this B. Sacrament vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thilie, <hi>there are among you weake and feeble, and many ſleepe,</hi> that is dye. How then oughtſt thou to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare thy ſelfe? Knowing that this
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:26101:95"/>B. Sacrament, as it giueth ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall health, life, &amp; nourriture to them that receaue it worthilie, ſo it alwaies bringeth death of the ſoule to them, that receaue it vnworthilie, &amp; ſometimes death of the bodie alſo, yea and eternall death of ſoule and body, vnles they repent in time.</p>
               <p>O my ſoule! <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> the Angels com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe the Altar, when the Prieſt offereth this dread ſacrifice, and they compaſſe thee alſo, when thou receiueſt it, and they waite at this Table, and vpon this King of glorie with great feare and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence, and goeſt thou to this Table as boldie as to an ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>not diſcerning the bodie of our Lord:</hi> not putting a difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt it and other meates? O Lord when I thinke of theſe things, to wit, of myne owne vnworthines, and thy worth and Maieſtie, I am
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:26101:95"/>affraid to approach ſo neere vnto thee; and if thou didſt not inuite me to come, I ſhould neuer dare to come in thy preſence, much leſſe to receaue thee into my breaſt; I ſhould ſaye with S.
<note place="margin">Luc. 5.</note> Pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>Goe forth from me, becauſe I am a ſinfull man, o Lord.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Cor. 6.</note> I ſhould ſaie with S. Paule, <hi>what participation hath Iuſtice with iniquitie. Or what ſocietie is there betwixt light and dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knes?</hi> what proportion betwixt thy light and my darknes, my ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenes and thy Maieſtie, thy ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctitie and my ſinnes? But what ſhall I doe, ô Lord? If I approach not to this Holie Sacrament, I ſhall ſhew my ſelf vnmanerlie, thou hauing ſo courteouſlie inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted me, yea diſobedient, thou not onely inuiting, but alſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunding mee.
<note place="margin">Io. 6.</note> If I come not to this feaſt I ſhall ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rue for hunger; If I drinke not of this fountaine
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:26101:96"/>of grace I ſhall dye for thirſt; If I come not to this ſunne I ſhal liue in darknes; If I come not to this fire I ſhall ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uer for cold; If I eate not of <hi>this bread of life,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Io. 6.</note> I amea dead man, and yet conſidering my vnworthines, I dare not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach to this worthie of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies, conſidering my impuritie I dare not come to this, <hi>ſpeculum ſine macula,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sap. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>this glaſſe without ſpotte.]</hi> Conſidering my prophanes, I dare not touch this <hi>Holie of Holies,</hi> conſidering my bafenes, I dare not appeare before ſuch maieſtie.</p>
               <p>O my ſweete Sauiour, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> thou woldſt haue thy Prieſt, (by reaſon that he muſt conſecrate &amp; touch this B. Sacrament) to be conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated, his fingers in his ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to be anointed with holy oyle, the chalice to be conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, the Altar, corporalls, Altar clothes, the Prieſts veſtments,
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:26101:96"/>yea the Church and all to be hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, for the reference and reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect they haue to this B. Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: Conſecrate, I beſeech thee, and ſanctifie me by thy grace, this Sacrament being inſtituted for me, not for thoſe other things, &amp; I being to receaue it ſacramental<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, and ſpirituallie, as thoſe other things can not receaue it. And ſeeing that thou commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deſt me to receaue it, giue me grace to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue it worthilie. Thou who commandeſt the end, giue the meanes.</p>
               <p>Thy Bleſſed Virgin-Mother was to receaue thee but once into her ſacred wombe, and yet, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> o Lord, how didſt thou ſanctifie her? how didſt thou prepare her? with what grace, puritie, and ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctitie, didſt thou endew her? San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie me, o Lord, by thy grace, cleanſe me from ſinne, purge
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:26101:97" rendition="simple:additions"/>me from all, euen veniall ſinnes, ſeeing I am not to receaue thee once onlie, but often and many times.</p>
               <p>Thou wouldeſt after thy death, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> haue thy dead body to be buried in a new monument, wherein none had beene buried before; to be laied in a winding ſheete of fine and cleane laune; and wilt thou permit me to receaue the ſame body now not dead, but li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing and glorified, into the graue and monume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of an old &amp; foule ſoule and body, in which the world, flesh, &amp; deuill haue been lodged by inordinat affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? wilt thou laie this thy glorified body in the foule linne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of a defiled ſoule? ô purge me, ô cleanſe mee, ô renew mee, that I maye be a new monument, a cleane ſyndon, to receaue thine, now not dead, but liuing, but immortall and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:26101:97"/>body.</p>
               <p>O doe not caſt ſuch <hi>Margarites before hoggs.</hi> Thou ſhalt,
<note place="margin">Matth 7</note> if thou do not waſh me from ſinne; O doe not permit me to ſitte downe to this feaſt without my nuptiall garment of charitie; I ſhall, vnles thou reſtore it, and put it on a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine.</p>
               <p>None but the high Prieſt in the old lawe might enter into <hi>Sancta Sanctorum, the Holies of Holies,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 30. Hebr. 9.</note> and he alſo but once a yeare, and this by reaſon of the Ark of the old law, where thou waſt preſent in figure; and ſhall I not ſo much enter into thee the <hi>Sancta Sancto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> and the Ark of the new law, as to let thee enter into mee, thou being the veritie of that figure?
<note place="margin">Exod. 30.</note> Moyſes though a chose<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of thine, was forbidden to approach to the buſh that burned, but conſumed nor, vntill he had put
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:26101:98"/>of his ſhooes; and ſhall I preſume to come to this B. Sacrament, and thy ſacred bodie in it, the veritie of that figure, and which burneth with the Diuinitie, yet is neuer conſumed, vnles I firſt laye aſide the ſhooes of all carnall affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s? The Prieſts of the old law were forbidden to aſcend to the Altar to offer their carnall Sacrifices be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they had waſhed themſelues in the <hi>brazen lauer.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 30</note> And ſhall I dare to approach to the Altar, &amp; to this ſo holy a Sacrifice and Sacrament, before I be rinſed in the lauer of penance, with the waters of contrition? S. Iohn Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſte, of whom thou thy ſelf, o Lord, pronounced, that,
<note place="margin">Luc. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>a greater Prophet among the children of woeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> then Iohn Baptiſt there was none;</hi> thought himſelf not worthie to vnlooſe the latcher of thy ſhooes;
<note place="margin">Mat 8.</note> The Centurion deemed him
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:26101:98"/>ſelfe not worthie to receaue thee into his howſe, which yet, as it is likelie was cleanlie ſwept &amp; rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie adorned, and ſhall I thinke my ſelf ſo worthie, as to touch not thy ſhooe ſtri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs, but thy ſacred bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, and to receaue thee into mee who am defiled both in body &amp; ſoule.
<note place="margin">Iob. 25.</note> 
                  <hi>The starres are not cleane in thy ſight,</hi> and how ſhall I dare to appeare before thy diuine eyes more bright then the Sunne it ſelfe, I being no ſtarre, but rather a candle put out and ſmoakie?</p>
               <p>Salomon, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> when he had built for thee, o Lord, that goodlie Temple, the maſter peece of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonrie, and had adorned it with gold, ſiluer, and precious ſtones, yet he thought it no fitte place for thee, and therefore ſaied;
<note place="margin">2 Paral. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>Ergone credibile eſt vt habitet Deus cum ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minibus ſuper terram? Si coelum &amp; coeli coelornm, non te capiunt, quanto
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:26101:99"/>magis domus ista quam aedificaui; Is it cred<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bile then that God should dwell with men vpon the earth? If heauen and the heauens of heauens, do not take thee, how much more this houſe, which I haue built?</hi> And ſhall I whoſe bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy is made but of mudde, and whoſe ſoule is defiled with ſinne, thinke my ſelf a fitte pallace for thy maieſtie? O Lord I am not worthie the ayre I breath, the ground I ſtand on, the bread I eate, the wine or water I drink, how then can I be worthie of this B. Sacrament, which I am to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue, and which is the greateſt benefite thou euer beſtowedſt on man, becauſe this guift is as good as thy ſelfe, who art the guift, and the giuer. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> 
               </p>
               <p>And yet thou wilt haue me to receaue it at thy Prieſts hands; and receaue it I may, ſeeing thou haſt ſo ordained, but vnles thou, who
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:26101:99"/>giueſt it, giue me alſo worthines, I can not receaue it worthilie. Thou therefore who inuiteſt me to this holie Sacrament, and forbiddeſt men to receaue it vnworthilie, vouchſafe to giue me that grace, that reuerence, that deuotion, which may make mee worthie. It is thy deſire that I ſhould come worthilie, &amp; it is alſo my deſire; &amp; ſeeing that I can neither fulfill thy deſire, nor my deſire, but by thy grace, I beſeech thee grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t me the grace to fulfill thy deſire, and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I ſhall fulfill my deſire, which is to receaue this Holy Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thilie; and although by thy grace I receaue thee worthilie, yet giue me the humilitie, alwayes to thinke my ſelf, of my ſelfe, vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie: for the more I eſteeme my ſelfe vnworthie, the more by thee I ſhall be eſteemed worthie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="meditation">
               <pb n="152" facs="tcp:26101:100" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>THE 12. MEDITATION <hi>VVith what loue to our Sauiour we should receaue this B. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament?</hi>
               </head>
               <p>VVHEN thou haſt, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> O my ſoule, by the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions alleadged in the former me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation, ſtirred vp thy ſelfe to a fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liall feare and reuerence, thou muſt alſo endeauour to moue thy ſelfe to a feruent loue, and charitie towards thy Sauiour, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou art to receaue. To this all thy former meditations will conduce; for that by them is ſhewed what a good houſe keeper, how liberall
<pb facs="tcp:26101:100" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26101:101" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb n="153" facs="tcp:26101:101" rendition="simple:additions"/>an Hoſte, what a Father, what a Mother, what a Friend, Spouſe, Phiſitian and Paſtour (all which are titles of loue) Chriſt hath ſhewed himſelf vnto the in this B. Sacrament.</p>
               <p>Saye then vnto him: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> thou haſt ſhewed they ſelf in this B. Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment a noble houſe keeper, giue me the loue belonging to one of thy familie: thou haſt ſhewed thy ſelfe a bountifull Hoſte, giue me the loue of a louing gueſt; thou haſt ſhewed thy ſelfe a Father and Mother, make me a louing and obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t childe; Thou haſt ſhewed thyſelfe a louinge friend, make me loue thee reciprocallie, yea a Spouſe make me a louing ſpouſe, yea a Phiſitian, make me a louing patient, yea a Paſtour, inflame my heart with the loue of a louing ſheepe.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thou neuer ſhewedſt more loue
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:26101:102"/>to mee then in this B. Sacrament, by which, out of a great loue, thou giueſt to me, and after ſo admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble a manner (as loue is ingenious) thy bodie, bloud, ſoule and diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie. By Incarnation; thou im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partedſt thy ſelf onlie to that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture which thou tookeſt of the B. Virgin; But by this Sacrament, thou beſtoweſt thyſelf on all in particular, who receaue it. VVith what loue ſhall I paye this loue? Thou giueſt thy <hi>All</hi> vnto me, and can I giue leſſe then my <hi>All</hi> to thee? and yet ſo ſhall I not rendre like for like, becauſe my <hi>All</hi> is nothing to thy <hi>All,</hi> nothing ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as if a begger ſhould giue his raggs for the Kinges purple robe, crowne, ſcepter, and king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
               <p>I vſe to take kindelie all which a freind giueth, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> be it but a ring, or Image, becauſe I imagine that
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:26101:102"/>he giueth his loue in his guift, yea and himſelf alſo in his guift, though not in perſon; with what loue then ſhould I anſwer to thy loue, who giueſt thy ſelfe vnto me not onelie in thy guifts and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, as thou giueſt by creation iuſtification, and glorification, but alſo by this B. Sacrament in thine owne perſon? Children loue their parents and nurces, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they feed and nouriſh them: brute beaſts loue them, who giue them meate, be it but cruſtes and bones, hay or ſtrawe: how then ſhould I loue thee, O Lord, who feedeſt me with thy owne fleſh &amp; bloud; ſeaſoned and ſauced with the Diuinitie. O my heart to ſhew thy ſelf that thou art not made of flint, marble, or ſteele, but of ſoft fleſh, reſolue thy ſelf into loue for thy Sauiours loue ſhewed in this B. Sacrament, and
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:26101:103"/>being ſo reſolued, and transfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, imploy thy ſelfe and all thou are for his loue and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour.</p>
               <p>If thou thus prepare thy ſelfe by a great reuerence and loue to this B. Sacrament, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> in which the Sonne of God reſideth, as in his cabinet, not onely he, but his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther alſo the firſt perſon in Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and their holy Spirit the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Ghoſt, the third perſon, who procedeth from them both, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiall and coequall vnto them, will all three come vnto thee, not onely to viſit thee, but alſo to dwell with thee: for this God the So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne promiſeth ſaying; <hi>If any loue me he will keepe my word,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioa. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>and my Father will loue him, and we will come to him, and will make abode with him:</hi> And becauſe thou art notable of thyſelf to furniſh thy howſe ſo, as it may be fitt for the
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:26101:103"/>entertainement of ſo great per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonages, they will bring with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their tapiſtrie and ornaments of grace and vertues, by which thou ſhalt be adorned to their liking; And becauſe thou canſt not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare a feaſt worthie ſuch gueſts, though thou ſhouldeſt ſeeke ſea and Land for it, they will bring their feaſt with them, to witt this Bleſſed Sacrament, the <hi>Manna</hi> which conteineth all that can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light thy ſpirit, and with it they will bring abounda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of all grace, by which they will feaſt thee, and will be feaſted of thee.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="meditation">
               <pb n="158" facs="tcp:26101:104"/>
               <head>THE 13. MEDITATION <hi>To be made immediatlie after Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion: How than<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>kefull the Receauer should bee.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>VVHen thou haſt receaued this B. Sacrament, pauſe awhile, and think what thou haſt receaued, Thou haſt receaued more then the worth of Heauen and earth, the Sonne of God, <hi>in whom be all the treaſures of wiſedom and knowledge hidden:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Coloſſ. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>in whom dwelle the fulneſse of the God head cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porallie, who is the head of all princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>palitie and power,</hi> thou haſt recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued him, who is worth ſo much
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:26101:104"/>that he is ineſtimable, no price ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be ſett on him. <hi>Antonius</hi> and <hi>Cleo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patra</hi> did on a time vainlie ſtriue, who ſhould make the greateſt feaſt; And <hi>Antonius</hi> prepared all that Sea and Land could affoard: <hi>Cleopatra</hi> not ſollicitous for any ſuch fare, tooke an vnion which hung at her eare, and reſoluing it drank it at a draft; and putting her finger to the other eare, to take another vnion, he, who was elected arbiter and Iudge betwixt them, bad <hi>Cleopatra</hi> hold her hand for that ſhe had alreadie ſurpaſſed <hi>Antonius</hi> his feaſt, hauing drunk alreadie the price of all Egypt. But thou O my ſoule, by recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing this B. Sacrament eateſt and drinkeſt at once, the bodie and bloud of Chriſt (for with his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, his bloud alwayes is by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comitance and inſeparable vnio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) which is more then the price of
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:26101:105"/>Egypt, yea the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a thouſand worlds, And therefore if thou ſhouldeſt reſolue thy heart into gratitude and thankes giuing, thou coulds not ſhew ſufficient gratitude for this ſo great benefit.</p>
               <p>Say then to thy bountifull Ieſus with gratefull Dauid;
<note place="margin">Pſa. 115.</note> 
                  <hi>Quid retri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buam Domino pro omnibus quae retri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buit mihi? what shall I render to our Lord for all things that he hath ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred to me?</hi> nay what ſhall I render to my Lord for this onlie thing which he hath beſtowed on mee? thou haſt ô Lord, not onlie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed on mee great benefites, and this the greatieſt of all<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> but thou haſt alſo rendred good for euill, mercie and grace for my ſinnes, what can I render thee for this?
<note place="margin">Pſa. 115.</note> I will follow King Dauids counſell: <hi>I will take the chalice of ſaluation and I will inuocate the name of our Lord:</hi> I will take the chalice
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:26101:105"/>of thy Paſſion, which thou didſt drink on the Croſſe, &amp; I will offer that ſacrifice for this, and both for all thy benefites, and by them I will inuocate and praiſe thy name for euer.</p>
               <p>If I could ſpeake at once with all the tongues of men and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, I could not, ô Lord, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> giue thee ſufficient thanks for this ſo great a benefit, which conteineth thy ſacred ſelf, and thy holie fleſh and blood, Deifyed by thy Diuinitie. VVherefore in an aſtoniſhment at this great benefit, and thy great liberalitie, I will be ſilent, and by my ſilence I will teſtifie and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe that thou haſt beſtowed on me in this B. Sacrament more then tongue can expreſſe, yea more then heart can conceaue.</p>
               <p>But although I can not giue thee, O Lord, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> any thing of mine owne (though heauen and earth
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:26101:106"/>were mine owne) which can haue any proportion with this thy ſo great guift, yet I can pay thee with thine owne ſufficientlie. O eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Father, thou haſt giuen me a guift equiualent to this great be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit, and with this I can pay thee, though I pay thee with thy owne. And what is that? It is thine owne Sonne Chriſt Ieſus, God &amp; man, whom thou beſtoweſt on mee in this B. Sacrament, &amp; him I render againe vnto thee for this and all thy benefites. He is thine, I know, by eternall generation, becauſe by that he was borne conſubſtantiall to thee, but he is myne alſo by te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall generation, becauſe by that he is borne conſubſtantiall to me, and he is mine again by this holie communion, and in a manner as much mine,
<note place="margin">Io. 6.</note> as the meat I eate &amp; the drinke I drinke: <hi>becauſe his flesh is trulie meate, and his bloud is
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:26101:106"/>trulie drink.</hi> I therefore render vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, ô Eternall Father, thy owne ſonne, whom thou haſt giuen to me, and I render him not onelie for thy other benefites, but alſo and eſpeciallie for this, which by communion of this B. Sacrament I haue receaued at thy bountifull hands.</p>
               <p>And although in ſo doeing I giue thee but thine owne, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> yet I giue thee alſo mine, and him who is twiſe myne, by Incarnation, and by this Holy communion, yea as often mine, as I communicate. And this guift, which I offer to thee in thankes giuing for this &amp; all thy benefites, thou will not, thou canſt not refuſe;
<note place="margin">Matth 3 &amp; 17.</note> becauſe it is thy well beloued So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne, <hi>in whom thou art well pleaſed.</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> 
               </p>
               <p>And if thou wilt haue alſo of myne, I offer thee all I can &amp; haue; I offer thee my hart, and that alſo
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:26101:107" rendition="simple:additions"/>inflamed with loue, and in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner (as I deſire it ſhould be) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued into loue of thee, and all I am and haue by thy grace, ſhall be hereafter for thee and thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice.</p>
               <p>If my tongue ſpeake hereafter, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> it ſhall ſpeake of thee, who haſt made it the bridge, by which thou haſt made thine entrie into mee. If I think of any thing, it ſhall be of thee, who now art ſo preſent an obiect, that thou art not onelie by mee, but alſo in mee. If I doe any thing, it ſhall be by thy dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, who now art in me to direct me in all my actions, as my firſt Moouer. If I liue, I will liue by thee &amp; in thee, becauſe now thou liueſt in mee to make me liue hereafter thy life, not my owne former life; that ſo I may ſay with S. Paul; <hi>viuo ego, iam non ego, viuit vero in me Christus:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>I liue now, not I,
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:26101:107"/>but Chriſt liueth in me.</hi> If I loue any thing hereafter, it ſhall be thee or for thee, for thou <hi>haſt first loued me,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Ioan. 4.</note> and beſt loued me, and by this B. Sacrament thou haſt ſhewed thy ſelf my greateſt benefactour, my greateſt friend and louer, Thou therefore here after ſhalt haue me for thy ſeruant.</p>
               <p>Thou hereafter ſhalt haue my loue, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> for that I can neuer beſtow my ſelf better then on thee; I can neuer beſtow my loue on a better obiect then thee, who art <hi>Summum bonum,</hi> cheefeſt good; good by eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and not good onelie in thy ſelf, but good to me by creation, by which thou giueſt me my na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall being; by iuſtification, by which thou giueſt me a ſuperna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall being; and by this B. Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by which thou giueſt thy owne being, to witt thy bodie, bloud, ſoule and diuinitie, of
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:26101:108"/>which thou conſiſteſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="meditation">
               <head>THE 14. MEDITATION <hi>How the Communicant or Receiuer is enriched by this B. Sacrament, and ſo should litle eſteeme all worldlie loſſes.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>COnſider how much thou art enriched by this precious Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> more then if thou wert Emperour, not only of this terreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triall, but alſo of the Celeſtiall world, for thou poſſeſſeſt him by receiuing this B. Sacrament, who is more worth then all that is in heauen or Earth, yea then all that can be, but God. For he whom
<pb facs="tcp:26101:108" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26101:109" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb n="167" facs="tcp:26101:109"/>thou receaueſt is the Sonne of God, conſubſtantiall and equall to his Father, and his bodie and blood which he beſtoweth on thee in this Holy Sacrament by reaſon of their vnion with the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinitie, are more precious then all that is in heauen and earth. If eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie prayer or good worke of Chriſt was more worth then a worlds redemption, if euerie drop of his blood is of that value, that it could haue redeemed a thouſand worlds, of what worth and value is whole Chriſt, whom thou who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie receiueſt?</p>
               <p>O my God, ô my Sauiour, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> what bountie is this, to beſtow ſo much on me, ſo poore a creature, &amp; who haue ſo litle deſerued at thy ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds? I ſhould call it prodigalitie, but that thou canſt not be prodigall, becauſe thou canſt not giue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue thy ſtate and meanes: O
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:26101:110"/>my ſoule how happie wert thou, if thou kneweſt, or couldeſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue thy riches and happines: As therefore an Emperour of the whole world would not care if ſome litle cottage ſhould be burnt or taken from him, becauſe it is nothing to the whole world, which he poſſeſſeth; ſo hereafter if God ſhould permit aſmuch to be taken from thee, as was taken from Iob; if thou looſe lands and goods, kinsfolkes, friends, and all; if thou ſuffer domage in thy fame, honour, or libertie; if thou be neuer ſo poore for worldlie wealth; If thou bee neuer ſo croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with aduerſities, ſay with Iob: <hi>Our Lord,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iob. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>hath giuen, and our Lord hath taken away, as it hath pleaſed our Lord,</hi> ſo is it done; the name of our Lord be bleſſed.</p>
               <p>Say vnto thy God though thou make me as poore as Iob, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> thou
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:26101:110"/>shalt take nothing from me but that which thou gaueſt me, and beſides in this B. Sacrament thou haſt giuen me that which is more worth then all thou cauſt take from me, to witt thy ſelf, body bloud, ſoule and diuinitie: which whileſt I poſſeſſe, I can not be poore, looſe I neuer ſo much, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I poſſeſſe thee, who art all riches; which whileſt I poſſeſſe I can not be miſerable, I can not be but happie, though all the miſeries of the world ſhould fall at once vpon me; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, I poſſeſſe thee who art the bliſſe of men and Angels. If then I want temporall goods, if I want health of bodie, if aduerſities croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe me, giue me o Lord grace to beare all patientlie, and not to think what I haue loſt, but what I haue gotten by receiuing thee in this B. Sacrament, to which
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:26101:111"/>all I can looſe is nothing.</p>
               <p>Thou rainedſt ô Lord, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 
                  <hi>Manna</hi> vpon the Iewes which <hi>was like the ſeed of a Coriander,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 16.</note> and yet the Iewes were ſo gratefull for it that they cried, <hi>Manha,</hi> what is this what largeſſe, what riches doth God raine on vs? and yet that was but as a crumme which felle from thy Table. But now thou rayneſt on me by meanes of this B Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, not a crumme of bread, but the whole <hi>bread of life,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioa. 6.</note> the whole feaſt, thy only begotten Sonne, &amp; with him the riches of his diuini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and humanitie, which are ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimable. <hi>Manha,</hi> what is this? what a precious guift is this? what bountie is this? That manna was ſo precious, ſo delicious, that it made the Iewes for a time to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne their fleſh pots of Eg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pt. This <hi>Manna</hi> of the B Sacrament, the veritie of that figure, hath all
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:26101:111"/>delights that the ſpirituall appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite can deſire.</p>
               <p>I therefore will heerafter con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne all worldlie and carnall pleaſures, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> all the riches the world can afford, as only fleſh pots of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gipt, and will co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent my ſelf with this <hi>Manna</hi> onlie, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth all ſpirituall delight, and which in a litle roome containeth more then the price of heauen &amp; earth. O my ſoule if thou wilt play the wiſe marchant, ſell all, giue all, looſe all for this pretious Margarite, this Holy and moſt rich Sacrament, and when thou haſt it, as thou haſt it ſo often as thou receiueſt it, deſire no more, it is enough to content an infinite appetite, becauſe it is infinite in all goodnes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="meditation">
               <pb n="172" facs="tcp:26101:112" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>THE 15. MEDITATION <hi>How by the Receiuing of this B. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament the receiuer is made the Temple of God.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Foundation of thy Te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> ô my ſoule, is thy faith which is the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d work of all ſpirituall buildi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, The walles are thy hope, which erecteth thy minde and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leuareth it to heauen, The roofe is Charitie, which ſheltreth thee from the winds and tempeſts of all temptations, and <hi>couereth the multitude of thy ſinnes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Pet 4.</note> and hideth
<pb facs="tcp:26101:112" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26101:113" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb n="173" facs="tcp:26101:113" rendition="simple:additions"/>them from the ſight of God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it quite effaceth them, The Biſhop who conſecrateth this thy Temple, is Chriſt Ieſus, the high Prieſt &amp; Biſhop of the new lawe, and his preſence is the conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the Altar is thy hart, the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice is the ſacred body &amp; bloud of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>The Temple of Salomon was eſteemed ſo holie, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> that God pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred it before all other places in the world, and tooke more plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in it, and heard the prayers that were made in it more willin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glie then in any other place, And yet thou (o my ſoule) by receiuing this B. Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t art made a more holy Temple then that was. That was an vnliuing and inanimat Temple, thou a liuing temple, in that was the propitiatorie, in thee is the propitiatour himſelf, who alſo is a <hi>propitiation for our ſinnes:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Ioa 2.</note> in
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:26101:114"/>that were two pictures or ſtatues of two Cherubins, in thee is the Lord of Cherubins, &amp; Seraphins, and of all the Angels, who as S. Chriſoſtome affirmeth do waite and attende in troupes with all reuerence on their Lord when the Prieſt conſecrateth, and he and thou receaueſt this Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t; for where the King is, there are his courtiours; In that Temple was <hi>the glorie of God</hi> which was but a cloud which filled the Temple,
<note place="margin">2. Paral. 17.</note> &amp; was onlie a figure and repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God his diuinitie, in thee is Chriſt Ieſus God and man the <hi>ſplendour of his Fashers glorie</hi> and veritie of that figure;
<note place="margin">Hebr. 1.</note> in that were <hi>golden candleſticks</hi> on which were lights to illuminate the Temple,
<note place="margin">2. Par. 4.</note> in this is Chriſts humanitie, which was the candleſtick that bare the light of the Diuinitie, and ſhewed it to the world. In that Temple
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:26101:114"/>were the figuratiue Prieſts who offered the figuratiue Sacrifices of the old Law, in thee is the high Prieſt of the newe lawe Chriſt Ieſus, who offered himſelf in a bloudie manner on the Croſſe, &amp; in an vnbloudie manner in the Sacrament which is in thee: That Temple was veſted and limmed with pure gold, thou art adorned with a richer gold, Charitie, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which thou canſt not be the Temple of God.</p>
               <p>O my Soule ſeing that by this B. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Sacrament thou art made the Temple of God, behaue thy ſelf, comport thyſelf, be like his holy Temple. A Te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple is inſtituted to worſhip &amp; honour God, by ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces pſalmes &amp; prayers, be thou ſuch a te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple; let the ſacrifices of prayer, thankeſgiuing, of a contrite he art be alwaies offered in thee; Offer vnto him daily an holocauſt of
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:26101:115"/>thy ſelf by a perfect reſignation, and denyall of thy ſelf: offer in this thy Temple,
<note place="margin">Mar. 11</note> daylie prayer, for his howſe and Temple <hi>is the houſe of praier,</hi> offer vnto him this Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of his ſacred body and bloud which thou haſt receiued. Te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples and Churches are ſwept cleanlie, and adorned richlie; let then no vncleane thinge be in thee, no mortall ſinne, yea (aſmuch as hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main frailtie will permit) noe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall ſinne, noe carnall, no world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie cogitatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s or affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. Sweepe the Temple of thy Soule from all ſuch fylth and duſt, nay waſh it with the teares of contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<note place="margin">Mar. 11</note> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all ſuch ordure. VVhippe out (as Chriſt did out of the Iewes Temple) all buyers and ſellers, all mortall ſinnes, by which thou buyeſt at a deare rate the world and its pleaſures, and ſelleſt thy ſelf to the deuill for a vaine plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:26101:115"/>or a litle traſhe; Let thy Temple rather be adorned with faith, hope, charitie, &amp; all manner of vertues, with chaſt, pure, and holy cogitations, with the ſeauen guifts of the holy Ghoſt,
<note place="margin">Eſa 11.</note> and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciallie let it be guilded with the Gold of Charitie; That God one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, whoſe Temple now thou art, may be honoured, prayſed, and loued by thee.</p>
               <p>If thou thus ſweepe, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> cleanſe &amp; adorne thy Temple, God will willinglie dwell in thee, as in his owne proper pallace, as in his owne houſe and home: for this is his deſire,
<note place="margin">Prou. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>whoſe delights are to be with the children of men.</hi> But as he deſireth to lodge and dwell in thee, ſo muſt thou alſo deſire his companie, for he will not be an vnwellcome gueſt. thou muſt take heede, leaſt by any ſinne thou ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell or diſguſt him, for he is light
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:26101:116"/>and cannot conſort with ſuch darknes, thou muſt therefor en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter taine him by chaſt and holy co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitations, and meditations and eſpeciallie by loue and charitie, for he hath ſhewed thee great loue in making thee by this B. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament his Temple, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore expecteth loue for loue.</p>
               <p>And now that thou haſt him dwelling with thee and in thee, lay hold on him, linke him to thee by the golden chaine of Charitie, leaue him not, and he will not leaue thee. Saye vnto him, as Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob ſayd vnto the Angell, who repreſented the perſon of God <hi>non dimittam te niſi benedixeris mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hi:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 32.</note> 
                  <hi>I will not let thee goe, vnleſse thou bleſse mee:</hi> and becauſe I will neuer want thy bleſſing, I will neuer let thee goe.
<note place="margin">2. Reg. 6</note> 
                  <hi>Obededon,</hi> and all his houſe was bleſſed with many a benediction for receiuing
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:26101:116"/>into it the Ark of the old law, &amp; ſhall not I, ô Lord, receiue many bleſſings by receiuing thy Sonne Chriſt Ieſus the Ark of the new law, &amp; the veritie of that figure? O let not this Arke bring fewer bleſſings with it, then that did.</p>
               <p>I deſire not the temporall bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing which Iſaac gaue to his ſonne Iacob, to wit, <hi>the dew of heauen,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 27</note> 
                  <hi>the fatnes of the earth, and aboundance of corne and wine.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epheſ 1</note> But I deſire the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nediction, by which thou <hi>hast bleſſed vs in all ſpirituall bleſsing in celeſtials.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luc. 2.</note> And ſeing that I now haue thee in my armes with Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meon, I deſire his benediction, that I may departe and dye in peace, with thee, and all thy Saints and Angels;
<note place="margin">Matth. 5</note> I deſire thoſe eight beatitudes &amp; bleſſings of <hi>pouertie in ſpirit,</hi> of <hi>meeknes,</hi> of <hi>mourning</hi> for my ſinnes, of <hi>hunger after Iuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice,</hi> of <hi>mercifulnes,</hi> of <hi>cleanes of
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:26101:117"/>heart,</hi> of <hi>peace making,</hi> of <hi>patient ſuffering perſecution for iustice ſake.</hi> And laſtlie I deſire thy eternall benediction which conſiſteth in the cleare viſion and fruition of thee, by which all the Angels and Saints are bleſſed, and this I moſt humblie craue and in a manner claime by vertue of that thy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe made to all worthie recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of this B. Sacrament,
<note place="margin">Io. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>He that eateth my flesh and drinketh my bloud hath life euerlasting, and I will raiſe him vp at the laſt daie.</hi> Beſtow on me then, ô Lord, a benediction of thy grace now, and after my death a benediction of thy glorie in the next life, where I ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e liue in bliſſe with thee and thy Saints for euer.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="meditation">
               <pb n="181" facs="tcp:26101:117"/>
               <head>THE 16. MEDITATION <hi>Of the good purpoſes which after Communion are to be made.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AFter that thou haſt receiued this B. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Sacrament and no leſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy Sauiours fleſh, blood, ſoule and diuinitie in it, to ſhew thyſelf gratefull for ſo great a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit and ſo noble a gueſt, thou ſhalt do well and pleaſinglie vnto him, if thou make theſe enſewi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g good purpoſes; for not onlie to do good, or to promiſe good, but euen to purpoſe what is good, is a diſpoſition to doing good and ſo pleaſing vnto him.</p>
               <pb n="182" facs="tcp:26101:118"/>
               <p>Say therefore vnto him: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> thou haſt vouchſafed to enter into mee by my mouth, as by the dore and gate of my houſe. <hi>This gate</hi> hereafter <hi>shall be shut</hi> (as was the Eaſtern gate of which Ezechiel ſpeaketh) <hi>It shall not be opened and men shall not paſse through it,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ezech. 44.</note> 
                  <hi>it shall be shut for the Prince.</hi> This gate, o Lord, ſhall be ſhut to all but thee the Prince, thou onelie ſhalt haue the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand for the opening or ſhutting of it. The world, fleſh, or deuill ſhall neuer enter by it, none but thou, or for thy ſake.</p>
               <p>And therefore hereafter my mouth ſhall neuer ſpeake but of thee, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> or things belonging to thee, and thy honour: It ſhall be opened onelie to praiſe thee, or to praye vnto thee,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 70.</note> 
                  <hi>Repleatur os meum laude vt ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tet gloriam tuam: let my mouth be filled with praiſe that I may ſing thy glorie.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epheſ. 4</note> 
                  <hi>All naughtie ſpeech let
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:26101:118"/>it not proceed from it.</hi> It is the gate of thy Temple, let no vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane thinge haue entrance by it. It is the gate of the Citie, keepe it ſhut, and fortifie it by thy grace that it may keepe out thy enemies and withſtand all the batterie &amp; aſſaults of their tentations: It hath been filled with thy ſacred bodie &amp; blood, let it here after be filled with praiſes of thy name &amp; tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing.</p>
               <p>And becauſe my tongue hath been the bridge by which thou haſt paſſed, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> and which thou haſt ſanctified with thy ſacred body, &amp; embrued, as it were with thy holy blood, I purpoſe neuer to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane it by idle &amp; vaine ſpeeches, much leſſe to pollute it by detra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, calumnious and reproche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſpeeches, by laſciuious talk, by lying, or ſwearing, or blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, but I will with thy grace
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:26101:119"/>exerciſe it hereafter in praiſing thy holy name, in praying to thee, in talking of thee, of thy life and death, of thy great benefites, and in particular of this B. Sacrament, which ſo often I haue receaued, of heauen and heauenlie things. And therefore hereafter I will not aduenture without thee to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne this voluble, variable and inconſtant creature, mooued with euerie winde like a reed: I could neuer gouerne it, and no meruaile becauſe <hi>Linguam nullus hominum domare poteſt.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>obi 3</note> 
                  <hi>No man can tame the tongue;</hi> thou only canſt becauſe <hi>Domini eſt gubernare lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guam,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prouerb 16.</note> 
                  <hi>it apperteineth to our Lord to gouerne the tongue,</hi> and ſo to thee I yeeld vp the rule of it, to thy dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction I commend it, that it may be ſilent whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou wouldeſt haue it be ſilent, and that it may ſpeake onelie, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou wouldeſt haue it
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:26101:119" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſpeake, and what thou wouldeſt haue it ſpeake.</p>
               <p>And becauſe thou, ô Lord, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> by this B. Sacrament art my noble &amp; faſt frie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d,
<note place="margin">See the med. 12.</note> I will neuer ſhake ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds with thy enemies the world, fleſh &amp; deuill, nor ſhall I loue any thing which is offenſiue to thee.
<note place="margin">See a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue med 12. Se me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit 12.</note> Thou by this holy Sacrament art my Father and Mother, I ſhall there<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore honour thee, feare thee, loue thee, obey thee. Thou art the lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing Spouſe of my ſoule, and the mariage betwixt it and thee is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummated by this B. Sacrament. I will therefore wed my ſelf to noe creature by inordinate affection; that were to play th' Adultereſſe, and to breake the bond of this ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred wedlock, nor will I loue any but thee, or for thee. And being married to ſo great an Emperour as thou art, and thereby made alſo of high and noble condition, who
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:26101:120"/>by ſinne before was baſe. I will putt on the Emperiall robes of holy conuerſation fit for thy ſpouſe; my old habit of my old baſe behauiour and conditions, I will laie aſide; I will become a new creature, and in thoughts, words, and deeds I will carrie myſelf no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie as becometh thy chaſt ſpouſe.</p>
               <p>Thou haſt feaſted me with the royal fare of thy ſacred fleſh and blood, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> which maketh me noble and of Princelie blood; I will therefore behaue my ſelf Prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like,
<note place="margin">Luc 14.</note> not as aſſaue to my paſſions, and ſenſualities, but as a Lord and commaunder ouer them; And as the Prodigall ſonne after that his Father receiued hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into grace, &amp; had feaſted him, neuer returned againe to his hoggiſh fare, ſo I being now fedde with heauenlie fare, will ſcorne hereafter to taſt any more of any worldlie or car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:26101:120"/>delights, the hoggiſh fare of ſinners. I ame by receiuing this <hi>Holie</hi> of <hi>Holies</hi> thy ſacred bodie &amp; bloud, ſanctified, conſecrated, &amp; dedicated to thee onlie, and to thy ſeruice, I will therefore neuer prophane myſelf again, I will neuer employ my ſelf to the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of the world, or fleſh, or deuill or to any but thee, or for thee. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> 
               </p>
               <p>The holie Chalice though it be but of earthlie metall, be it ſiluer or gold, yet it is oeuer im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed to any other vſe then to receiue thy ſacred blood. The Church after Conſecration is neuer vſed but for thy ſeruice. And ſhall I who am better conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated and ſanctified then they, becauſe I am more capable of Sanctitie then they, permitte my ſelf to be put to prophane vſes: I am by this Sacrament made the Temple of God, which is the
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:26101:121" rendition="simple:additions"/>houſe of prayer; thou then ô Lord ſhalt be onelie ſerued in this te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple, thou onelie ſhalt be honoured &amp; praiſed in it.</p>
               <p>Thy entrance into me hath ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified my bodie and all the partes of it, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> my ſoule, and all her powers, and faculties, all therefore that is in mee ſhall hereafter be emploied to thy honour and ſeruice. To my ſoule, and all that is in mee I will ſay with Dauid.
<note place="margin">Pſ 102</note> 
                  <hi>Benedicanima mea Domino, &amp; omnia quae intra me ſunt nomint ſancto e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us. My ſoule bleſse thou our Lord, and all things that are within me his holy name.</hi> My vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding do thou think and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate allwayes of him; my will do thou euer loue him; my memorie do thou euer remember his bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fites, and this B. Sacrament in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, which he hath beſtowed on mee; my eyes looke on heauen and this Bleſſed Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, where
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:26101:121"/>he is; my hands lift vp your ſelues in thankes giuing; my feete follow his ſteppes, &amp; traces, and exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples, which he hath giuen, becauſe I and you all are conſecrated and dedicated to him by receiuing this B. Sacrament.</p>
               <p>And if it be an vnworthie thing to caſt a conſecrated Chalice into the dirt, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> is it not fare more vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthie to defile hereafter my bodie and ſoule by ſinne, which are wholie conſecrated and dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to God. O my ſoule do not thou preſume to prophane that, which by God is ſanctified, leaſt he puniſh thee as a prophaner of holy things. VVherefore as my bodie and ſoule, and all the partes of my body, and faculties of my ſoule, by this B. Sacrament are conſecrated to thee; So, ô Lord, let them euer be, and ſo they ſhall be, if to my will thou ioyne thy
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:26101:122"/>will, and to my force thy grac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> this is now my mind and purpoſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and I deſire to die in this mind, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> with it, that at my death bein<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thus prepared, I may feed on th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſacred body and blood in the B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Sacrament by a worthie Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and by vertue of it, after m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> death may be admitted to feed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> on thy Diuinitie with their B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Saints in Heauen by a cleare vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and fruition of thee, the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and the Holie Ghoſt thre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> perſons, and one God to whom be all Honour, and glorie fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> euer.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:26101:122"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
